<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Shah Lab</title>
 <link href="http://shahlab.ca/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://shahlab.ca"/>
 <updated>2018-08-29T18:36:20+00:00</updated>
 <id>http://shahlab.ca</id>
 <author>
   <name>Sohrab P. Shah</name>
   <email>sshah@bccrc.ca</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Ali Bashashati</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Ali-Bashashati"/>
   <updated>2018-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Ali-Bashashati</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Adi Steif</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Adi-Steif"/>
   <updated>2018-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Adi-Steif</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hossein Farahani</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Hossein-Farahani"/>
   <updated>2018-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Hossein-Farahani</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Interpretable dimensionality reduction of single cell transcriptome data with deep generative models.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/29784946"/>
   <updated>2018-05-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/29784946</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;29784946&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single-cell RNA-sequencing has great potential to discover cell types, identify cell states, trace development lineages, and reconstruct the spatial organization of cells. However, dimension reduction to interpret structure in single-cell sequencing data remains a challenge. Existing algorithms are either not able to uncover the clustering structures in the data or lose global information such as groups of clusters that are close to each other. We present a robust statistical model, scvis, to capture and visualize the low-dimensional structures in single-cell gene expression data. Simulation results demonstrate that low-dimensional representations learned by scvis preserve both the local and global neighbor structures in the data. In addition, scvis is robust to the number of data points and learns a probabilistic parametric mapping function to add new data points to an existing embedding. We then use scvis to analyze four single-cell RNA-sequencing datasets, exemplifying interpretable two-dimensional representations of the high-dimensional single-cell RNA-sequencing data.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Camila de Souza</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Camila-DeSouza"/>
   <updated>2018-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Camila-DeSouza</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Interfaces of Malignant and Immunologic Clonal Dynamics in Ovarian Cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/29754820"/>
   <updated>2018-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/29754820</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;29754820&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High-grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSC) exhibits extensive malignant clonal diversity with widespread but non-random patterns of disease dissemination. We investigated whether local immune microenvironment factors shape tumor progression properties at the interface of tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes (TILs) and cancer cells. Through multi-region study of 212 samples from 38 patients with whole-genome sequencing, immunohistochemistry, histologic image analysis, gene expression profiling, and T and B cell receptor sequencing, we identified three immunologic subtypes across samples and extensive within-patient diversity. Epithelial CD8+ TILs negatively associated with malignant diversity, reflecting immunological pruning of tumor clones inferred by neoantigen depletion, HLA I loss of heterozygosity, and spatial tracking between T cell and tumor clones. In addition, combinatorial prognostic effects of mutational processes and immune properties were observed, illuminating how specific genomic aberration types associate with immune response and impact survival. We conclude that within-patient spatial immune microenvironment variation shapes intraperitoneal malignant spread, provoking new evolutionary perspectives on HGSC clonal dispersion.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sophia Chan</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Sophia-Chan"/>
   <updated>2018-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Sophia-Chan</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Matt Wiens</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Matt-Wiens"/>
   <updated>2018-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Matt-Wiens</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m an undergraduate student at Simon Fraser University, working through
a joint honours in Applied Mathematics and Engineering Physics. With
this degree I’m able to split my time pretty much evenly between (mostly
continuous) mathematics, theoretical physics, and electronics
engineering; the three combined feel like home for me, and I wouldn’t
have it any other way. I’ll likely be pursuing graduate studies after my
undergraduate degree, though I haven’t yet decided which field I’d like
to specialize in—for now I’m keeping an open mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I’m not studying for my courses, I enjoy working on projects,
hacking in hackathons, and competing in programming competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I copy-pasted this bio from my website, which you can find
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mattwiens.ca&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you like.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Yikan Wang</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Yikan-Wang"/>
   <updated>2018-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Yikan-Wang</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>TERT promoter mutation in adult granulosa cell tumor of the ovary.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/29449679"/>
   <updated>2018-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/29449679</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;29449679&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The telomerase reverse transcriptase (TERT) gene is highly expressed in stem cells and silenced upon differentiation. Cancer cells can attain immortality by activating TERT to maintain telomere length and telomerase activity, which is a crucial step of tumorigenesis. Two somatic mutations in the TERT promoter (C228T; C250T) have been identified as gain-of-function mutations that promote transcriptional activation of TERT in multiple cancers, such as melanoma and glioblastoma. A recent study investigating TERT promoter mutations in ovarian carcinomas found C228T and C250T mutations in 15.9% of clear cell carcinomas. However, it is unknown whether these mutations are frequent in other ovarian cancer subtypes, in particular, sex cord-stromal tumors including adult granulosa cell tumors. We performed whole-genome sequencing on ten adult granulosa cell tumors with matched normal blood and identified a TERT C228T promoter mutation in 50% of tumors. We found that adult granulosa cell tumors with mutated TERT promoter have increased expression of TERT mRNA and exhibited significantly longer telomeres compared to those with wild-type TERT promoter. Extension cohort analysis using allelic discrimination revealed the TERT C228T mutation in 51 of 229 primary adult granulosa cell tumors (22%), 24 of 58 recurrent adult granulosa cell tumors (41%), and 1 of 22 other sex cord-stromal tumors (5%). There was a significant difference in overall survival between patients with TERT C228T promoter mutation in the primary tumors and those without it (p = 0.00253, log-rank test). In seven adult granulosa cell tumors, we found the TERT C228T mutation present in recurrent tumors and absent in the corresponding primary tumor. Our data suggest that TERT C228T promoter mutations may have an important role in progression of adult granulosa cell tumors.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Kieran Campbell</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Kieran-Campbell"/>
   <updated>2017-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Kieran-Campbell</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a postdoctoral fellow at the Department of Statistics, University of British Columbia, and the Department of Molecular Oncology, BC Cancer Agency, where I’m supervised by Sohrab Shah and Alexandre Bouchard-Côté. My research focuses on Bayesian models and scalable inference for single-cell and cancer genomics. Previously I was a PhD student at Oxford University supervised by Chris Yau.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Engineered in-vitro cell line mixtures and robust evaluation of computational methods for clonal decomposition and longitudinal dynamics in cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/29044127"/>
   <updated>2017-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/29044127</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;29044127&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characterization and quantification of tumour clonal populations over time via longitudinal sampling are essential components in understanding and predicting the response to therapeutic interventions. Computational methods for inferring tumour clonal composition from deep-targeted sequencing data are ubiquitous, however due to the lack of a ground truth biological data, evaluating their performance is difficult. In this work, we generate a benchmark data set that simulates tumour longitudinal growth and heterogeneity by in vitro mixing of cancer cell lines with known proportions. We apply four different algorithms to our ground truth data set and assess their performance in inferring clonal composition using different metrics. We also analyse the performance of these algorithms on breast tumour xenograft samples. We conclude that methods that can simultaneously analyse multiple samples while accounting for copy number alterations as a factor in allelic measurements exhibit the most accurate predictions. These results will inform future functional genomics oriented studies of model systems where time series measurements in the context of therapeutic interventions are becoming increasingly common. These studies will need computational models which accurately reflect the multi-factorial nature of allele measurement in cancer including, as we show here, segmental aneuploidies.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Viktoria Bojilova</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Viktoria-Bojilova"/>
   <updated>2017-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Viktoria-Bojilova</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>LINE-1 retrotransposon-mediated DNA transductions in endometriosis associated ovarian cancers.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/29032825"/>
   <updated>2017-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/29032825</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;29032825&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Endometrioid (ENOC) and clear cell ovarian carcinoma (CCOC) share a common precursor lesion, endometriosis, hence the designation endometriosis associated ovarian cancers (EAOC). Long interspersed nuclear element 1 (LINE-1 or L1), is a family of mobile genetic elements activated in many cancers capable of moving neighboring DNA through 3’ transductions. Here we investigated the involvement of specific L1-mediated transductions in EAOCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through whole genome sequencing, we identified active L1-mediated transductions originating within the TTC28 gene in 34% (10/29) of ENOC and 31% (11/35) of CCOC cases. We used PCR and capillary sequencing to assess the presence of specific TTC28-L1 transductions in formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) blocks from six different anatomical sites (five tumors and one normal control) for four ENOC and three CCOC cases, and compared the results to the presence of single nucleotide variations (SNVs)/frame shift (fs) mutations detected using multiplex PCR and next generation sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TTC28-L1 mediated transductions were identified in at least three tumor samplings in all cases, and were present in all five tumor samplings in 5/7 (71%) cases. In these cases, KRAS, PIK3CA, CTNNB1, ARID1A, and PTEN mutations were found across all tumor sites while other selected SNV/fs mutations of unknown significance were present at varying allelic frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TTC28-L1 transductions along with classical driver mutations were near ubiquitous across the tumors, suggesting that L1 activation likely occurred early in the development of EAOCs. TTC28-L1 transductions could potentially be used to determine clonal relationships and to track ovarian cancer progression.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Join</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/misc/join"/>
   <updated>2017-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/misc/join</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;join-the-shah-lab&quot;&gt;Join the Shah Lab&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a number of ways that trainees and staff can join our lab and contribute to our mission, listed below.  Come to beautiful Vancouver, BC and help us advance our science!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graduate training&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Shah is affiliated with several graduate programs at UBC:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bioinformatics.ubc.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;UBC Bioinformatics Graduate Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsat.ubc.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;UBC Genome Sciences and Technology Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pathology.ubc.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;UBC Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cs.ubc.ca&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;UBC Department of Computer Science&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Fellows&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Interested post-doctoral fellows should send a cover letter, CV, transcripts, and contact information for 2-3 references to:&lt;br /&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:CareersMolOnc@bccrc.ca&quot;&gt;CareersMolOnc@bccrc.ca&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Professional staff and faculty&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Current opportunities:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://molonc.bccrc.ca/assistant-or-associate-professor-tenure-track-crc-tier-ii/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CRC Tier II Chair Opportunity in Dept of Molecular Oncology&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The driver landscape of sporadic chordoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/29026114"/>
   <updated>2017-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/29026114</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;29026114&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chordoma is a malignant, often incurable bone tumour showing notochordal differentiation. Here, we defined the somatic driver landscape of 104 cases of sporadic chordoma. We reveal somatic duplications of the notochordal transcription factor brachyury (T) in up to 27% of cases. These variants recapitulate the rearrangement architecture of the pathogenic germline duplications of T that underlie familial chordoma. In addition, we find potentially clinically actionable PI3K signalling mutations in 16% of cases. Intriguingly, one of the most frequently altered genes, mutated exclusively by inactivating mutation, was LYST (10%), which may represent a novel cancer gene in chordoma.Chordoma is a rare often incurable malignant bone tumour. Here, the authors investigate driver mutations of sporadic chordoma in 104 cases, revealing duplications in notochordal transcription factor brachyury (T), PI3K signalling mutations, and mutations in LYST, a potential novel cancer gene in chordoma.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Escape room photos</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/blog/escape"/>
   <updated>2017-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/blog/escape</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;7&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BZolINPjAVr/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Just destroyed the Studio room at i-Exit Vancouver, with 9 minutes to spare! #teambuilding #shahlab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A post shared by Shah Lab (@sohrabshahlab) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2017-09-29T17:55:09+00:00&quot;&gt;Sep 29, 2017 at 10:55am PDT&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Welcome</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/blog/welcome"/>
   <updated>2017-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/blog/welcome</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome! This is the new Sohrab P. Shah Lab website, based off &lt;a href=&quot;http://bedford.io&quot;&gt;Trevor Bedford’s&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://drummondlab.org/about.html&quot;&gt;D. Allan Drummond’s&lt;/a&gt; website template.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Prognostic Model to Predict Post-Autologous Stem-Cell Transplantation Outcomes in Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28898161"/>
   <updated>2017-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28898161</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28898161&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purpose Our aim was to capture the biology of classical Hodgkin lymphoma (cHL) at the time of relapse and discover novel and robust biomarkers that predict outcomes after autologous stem-cell transplantation (ASCT). Materials and Methods We performed digital gene expression profiling on a cohort of 245 formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tumor specimens from 174 patients with cHL, including 71 with biopsies taken at both primary diagnosis and relapse, to investigate temporal gene expression differences and associations with post-ASCT outcomes. Relapse biopsies from a training cohort of 65 patients were used to build a gene expression-based prognostic model of post-ASCT outcomes (RHL30), and two independent cohorts were used for validation. Results Gene expression profiling revealed that 24% of patients exhibited poorly correlated expression patterns between their biopsies taken at initial diagnosis and relapse, indicating biologic divergence. Comparative analysis of the prognostic power of gene expression measurements in primary versus relapse specimens demonstrated that the biology captured at the time of relapse contained superior properties for post-ASCT outcome prediction. We developed RHL30, using relapse specimens, which identified a subset of high-risk patients with inferior post-ASCT outcomes in two independent external validation cohorts. The prognostic power of RHL30 was independent of reported clinical prognostic markers (both at initial diagnosis and at relapse) and microenvironmental components as assessed by immunohistochemistry. Conclusion We have developed and validated a novel clinically applicable prognostic assay that at the time of first relapse identifies patients with unfavorable post-ASCT outcomes. Moving forward, it will be critical to evaluate the clinical use of RHL30 in the context of positron emission tomography-guided response assessment and the evolving cHL treatment landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Oleg Golovko</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Oleg-Golovko"/>
   <updated>2017-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Oleg-Golovko</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Alborz Mazloomian</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Alborz-Mazloomian"/>
   <updated>2017-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Alborz-Mazloomian</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Research</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/misc/research"/>
   <updated>2017-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/misc/research</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				Why do some cancer patients respond to treatment, while others succumb to their disease?  Why are some treatments effective initially, but fail over time?  How do cancer cells acquire the ability to spread from one part of the body to another?  These are the fundamental and unresolved questions which motivate cancer research worldwide.  Viewing cancer progression through the lens of evolutionary theory, our approach to addressing these problems centers on studying the genomes of cancer cells as fundamental units of information encoding biological properties.  We have an active research program across several interrelated major topics including: Cancer evolution, single cell genomics, mutational signatures and prediction of drug response. The primary activities in the lab consist of experimental design, large-scale cancer (epi)genomics/transcriptome data analytics, development of machine learning and Bayesian statistics methods and biological study of ovarian, breast and lymphoid cancers.
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cancer-evolution&quot;&gt;Cancer evolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img width=&quot;500&quot; class=&quot;pull-right&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/research/cancer_evolution.png&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				Our lab is motivated by studying cancer through the lens of evolution.  We are engaged in several studies that span both temporal and spatial multi-sample studies of our cancers of interest.  Observing the dynamics of genomically-defined clones reflected in timeseries biopsies of patient tumours, patient-derived xenografts, or through spreading of clones across anatomical sites is a key area of interest for our lab.  For example in recent work, we have identified clonal expansion patterns underpinning histological transformation in follicular lymphoma, mapped the spread of clones within the peritoneal cavity of ovarian cancers and identified reproducible clonal dynamics in patient derived breast cancer xenografts.   Our current questions relate to drug selection and the interplay between malignant cells and the tumour microenvironment.  
			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				Relevant recent work:&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/28249593&quot;&gt;ddClone: joint statistical inference of clonal populations from single cell and bulk tumour sequencing data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/27183439&quot;&gt;Clonal genotype and population structure inference from single-cell tumor sequencing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/27182968&quot;&gt;Divergent modes of clonal spread and intraperitoneal mixing in high-grade serous ovarian cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/25470049&quot;&gt;Dynamics of genomic clones in breast cancer patient xenografts at single-cell resolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/24633410&quot;&gt;PyClone: statistical inference of clonal population structure in cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/23780408&quot;&gt;Distinct evolutionary trajectories of primary high-grade serous ovarian cancers revealed through spatial mutational profiling&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bioinformatics-and-software-development&quot;&gt;Bioinformatics and software development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img width=&quot;500&quot; class=&quot;pull-right&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/research/bioinformatics_software.png&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				We invest heavily in developing robust analytical software for both internal and external use with broad distribution through open source repositories.
			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;	
				Relevant recent work:&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/28557980&quot;&gt;E-scape: interactive visualization of single-cell phylogenetics and cancer evolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/25060187&quot;&gt;TITAN: inference of copy number architectures in clonal cell populations from tumor whole-genome sequence data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/23383675&quot;&gt;DriverNet: uncovering the impact of somatic driver mutations on transcriptional networks in cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/24633410&quot;&gt;PyClone: statistical inference of clonal population structure in cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/28249593&quot;&gt;ddClone: joint statistical inference of clonal populations from single cell and bulk tumour sequencing data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/28750660&quot;&gt;ReMixT: clone-specific genomic structure estimation in cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/21625565&quot;&gt;deFuse: an algorithm for gene fusion discovery in tumor RNA-Seq data&lt;/a&gt;
				&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/22745232&quot;&gt;nFuse: discovery of complex genomic rearrangements in cancer using high-throughput sequencing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/22285562&quot;&gt;JointSNVMix: a probabilistic model for accurate detection of somatic mutations in normal/tumour paired next-generation sequencing data&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;single-cell-genomics-of-cancer&quot;&gt;Single cell genomics of cancer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img width=&quot;500&quot; class=&quot;pull-right&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/research/single_cell_genomics.png&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				The unit of evolutionary selection in cancer is the cell.  Extraordinary progress in measurement technologies has made it possible to reliably and accurately sequence the genomes of individual cancer cells at scale.  We have recently optimized biophysical techniques and hidden Markov model approaches to ascertain highly accurate copy number profiles of thousands of cancer cells.  As such, studying the ‘population genetics’ of cancer cells is a tractable goal.  We are developing phylogenetics and fitness computational models through measuring the population dynamics of thousands of individual cancer cells across timeseries, spatial samples and in the presence of genetic and pharmacologic intervention.  These experiments and computational methods are improving our knowledge of background mutation rates, properties of positive and negative selection (not observable in bulk samples) and how phylogenetic topologies reflect the relative fitness of clones. Furthermore, as we integrate multi-modal measurements, profiling the evolving malignant population in the context of its tumour microenvironment will be a strong interest of the lab.
			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				Relevant recent work:&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/28068316&quot;&gt;Scalable whole-genome single-cell library preparation without preamplification&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/27412862&quot;&gt;Robust high-performance nanoliter-volume single-cell multiple displacement amplification on planar substrates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/27183439&quot;&gt;Clonal genotype and population structure inference from single-cell tumor sequencing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/25470049&quot;&gt;Dynamics of genomic clones in breast cancer patient xenografts at single-cell resolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/28557980&quot;&gt;E-scape: interactive visualization of single-cell phylogenetics and cancer evolution&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mutational-signatures-in-dna-repair-deficient-cancers&quot;&gt;Mutational signatures in DNA repair deficient cancers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img width=&quot;500&quot; class=&quot;pull-right&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/research/mutational_signature.png&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				We recently published a landmark study showing how the genomes of ovarian cancer histotypes reflect the DNA repair abnormalities they harbour.  We are interested in how to optimize the computational discovery of genome-wide structural and point mutational signatures and how signatures can identify treatment opportunities for ovarian and breast cancers.  This work is being carried out at bulk and single cell resolution.  In addition, we are working in translation capacity to develop a robust genome-wide test to stratify ovarian cancers in the clinic.
			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				Relevant recent work:&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/28436987&quot;&gt;Genomic consequences of aberrant DNA repair mechanisms stratify ovarian cancer histotypes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/27182968&quot;&gt;Divergent modes of clonal spread and intraperitoneal mixing in high-grade serous ovarian cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/27161491&quot;&gt;The somatic mutation profiles of 2,433 breast cancers refines their genomic and transcriptomic landscapes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/26365879&quot;&gt;The genomic landscape of epithelioid sarcoma cell lines and tumours&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/25692284&quot;&gt;Multifocal endometriotic lesions associated with cancer are clonal and carry a high mutation burden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/22495314&quot;&gt;The clonal and mutational evolution spectrum of primary triple-negative breast cancers&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;selection-and-drug-response&quot;&gt;Selection and drug response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img width=&quot;500&quot; class=&quot;pull-right&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/research/drug_response.png&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				&quot;Making predictions is hard, especially about the future&quot; - Nils Bohr (and many other variants attributed to other famous people: Mark Twain, Nostradamus, Yogi Berra, etc…) .  We have a keen interest in learning fitness trajectories from timeseries study of cancer populations within controlled interventions such as CRISPR or pharmacologic methods as a means to predict response to drugs.  Using extensions of population genetics theory, we are interested in predicting how cell populations will respond in the presence of a perturbation.  This is indeed ‘hard’ and entails the need to decipher stochastic drift, clonal interaction and positive selection.  Furthermore, drug response may not be encoded in the genome, requiring dynamic state switching through the epigenome and reflected in the transcriptome.  What proportion of drug response can be explained through encoded mutations in the genome?  This remains unknown. We are pursuing integrative, multimodal molecular views over time in bulk tissues and single cells as  substrate to address this question.
			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				Relevant recent work:&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/28211448&quot;&gt;CX-5461 is a DNA G-quadruplex stabilizer with selective lethality in BRCA1/2 deficient tumours&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/26877821&quot;&gt;Identification of the epigenetic reader CBX2 as a potential drug target in advanced prostate cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/26530965&quot;&gt;Multifocal clonal evolution characterized using circulating tumour DNA in a case of metastatic breast cancer&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;key-collaborators&quot;&gt;Key collaborators&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				Vancouver:
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://molonc.bccrc.ca/aparicio-lab/&quot;&gt;Sam Aparicio&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://molonc.bccrc.ca/huntsman-lab/&quot;&gt;David Huntsman&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://obgyn.ubc.ca/person/jessica-mcalpine/&quot;&gt;Jessica McAlpine&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.msl.ubc.ca/faculty/hansen&quot;&gt;Carl Hansen&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stat.ubc.ca/~bouchard/&quot;&gt;Alexandre Cote-Bouchard&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://medgen.med.ubc.ca/person/marco-marra/&quot;&gt;Marco Marra&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bccrc.ca/dept/cflr/personnel/christian-steidl&quot;&gt;Christian Steidl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				Canada:
				&lt;a href=&quot;https://oicr.on.ca/investigators/lincoln-stein/&quot;&gt;Lincoln Stein&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;https://oicr.on.ca/investigators/paul-boutros/&quot;&gt;Paul Boutros&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://crchum.chumontreal.qc.ca/en/researchers/mes-masson-anne-marie&quot;&gt;Anne-Marie Mes-Masson&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcgill.ca/biochemistry/about-us/department/faculty-members/park&quot;&gt;Morag Park&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uhnresearch.ca/researcher/amit-m-oza&quot;&gt;Amit Oza&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
				International:
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cruk.cam.ac.uk/users/greg-hannon&quot;&gt;Greg Hannon&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cruk.cam.ac.uk/research-groups/caldas-group&quot;&gt;Carlos Caldas&lt;/a&gt;,
				&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/ravip/&quot;&gt;Ravi Pandya&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;funding-sources&quot;&gt;Funding sources&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;col-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;https://bccancerfoundation.com/&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/bccf-logo.svg&quot; alt=&quot;BC Cancer Foundation&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/193.html&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/cihr_logo-en.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CIHR&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cancer.ca/research&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/logo_ccs.png&quot; alt=&quot;CCSRI&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tfri.ca/&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/tfri-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;TFRI&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;col-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cancerresearchuk.org/&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/cruk-logo.svg&quot; alt=&quot;CRUK&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.standuptocancer.org/&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/stand-up-2-cancer.png&quot; alt=&quot;CSU2C&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.innovation.ca/&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/cfi-logo.svg&quot; alt=&quot;CFI&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genomecanada.ca&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/gc-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Genome Canada&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;col-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genomebc.ca/&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/genome-bc.png&quot; alt=&quot;Genome BC&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canarie.ca/&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/canarie-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;CANARIE&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chairs-chaires.gc.ca/home-accueil-eng.aspx&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/CRC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Canada Research Chairs&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.msfhr.org/&quot;&gt;
				&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/research/funding/MSFHR_logo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Michael Smith Foundation for Health Research&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; style=&quot;margin:0px 10px&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/a&gt;	
		&lt;/div&gt;		
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Shah Lab</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/misc/home"/>
   <updated>2017-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/misc/home</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Shah Lab at BC Cancer focuses on understanding the evolutionary principles by which cancers proliferate.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>About</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/misc/about"/>
   <updated>2017-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/misc/about</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-shah-lab&quot;&gt;The Shah Lab&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are a computational cancer biology lab interested in dissecting fundamental properties of cancer evolution.  We use high resolution genomics to study human cancers, coupling these measurements with innovation in computational methods to infer cancer biology at genome and single cell scales. The lab is led by Dr. Sohrab Shah, who is appointed as Associate Professor at UBC and Senior Scientist at BC Cancer.  He holds the Canada Research Chair in Computational Cancer Genomics and is a UBC Killam laureate. Our lab is located in beautiful Vancouver, BC at the BC Cancer Agency.  Our research overview can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/research&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and our papers are listed &lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/papers/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  If you are interested in joining the lab, please click &lt;a href=&quot;http://shahlab.ca/join.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more information about training and career opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Affiliations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://molonc.bccrc.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Department of Molecular Oncology, BC Cancer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pathology.ubc.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dept of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, UBC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cs.ubc.ca&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Department of Computer Science, UBC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bcgsc.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Michael Smith Genome Sciences Centre&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;b&gt; University of British Columbia &lt;/b&gt;

The UBC Faculty of Medicine provides innovative educational and research programs in the areas of health and life sciences through an integrated and province-wide delivery model. Most faculty positions are posted on the central [UBC recruitment site](https://webapps.hr.ubc.ca/hrjobs/jobpostings?facultydept=MEDF) and  [UBC Careers](http://www.hr.ubc.ca/careers/) --&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ReMixT: clone-specific genomic structure estimation in cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28750660"/>
   <updated>2017-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28750660</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28750660&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somatic evolution of malignant cells produces tumors composed of multiple clonal populations, distinguished in part by rearrangements and copy number changes affecting chromosomal segments. Whole genome sequencing mixes the signals of sampled populations, diluting the signals of clone-specific aberrations, and complicating estimation of clone-specific genotypes. We introduce ReMixT, a method to unmix tumor and contaminating normal signals and jointly predict mixture proportions, clone-specific segment copy number, and clone specificity of breakpoints. ReMixT is free, open-source software and is available at http://bitbucket.org/dranew/remixt .&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Contact</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/misc/contact"/>
   <updated>2017-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/misc/contact</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6&quot;&gt;
        &lt;address&gt;
	&lt;b&gt; BC Cancer Agency Research Centre&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
            675 West 10th Avenue&lt;br /&gt;
            Rm 4.108&lt;br /&gt;
            Vancouver, BC&lt;br /&gt;
            V5Z 1L3&lt;br /&gt;
            &lt;br /&gt;
	    Dr. Sohrab Shah &lt;br /&gt;
            Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:sshah@bccrc.ca&quot;&gt;sshah@bccrc.ca&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 
	    Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; onclick=&quot;window.open(&amp;quot;https://twitter.com/sohrabshah&amp;quot;);return false;&quot;&gt; @sohrabshah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	    &lt;br /&gt;
	    Administrative Coordinator &lt;br /&gt;
	    Jad Maanaki&lt;br /&gt;
	    Phone:+1 604.675.8209&lt;br /&gt;
	    Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Jmaanaki@bccrc.ca&quot;&gt;Jmaanaki@bccrc.ca&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 
        &lt;/address&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe class=&quot;pull-right&quot; src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2603.7237273648043!2d-123.12166164812054!3d49.26268218000623!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x548673c2cb8966bf%3A0x8120a7e52adbc3f2!2sBC+Cancer+Research+Centre!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sca!4v1499907753719&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border:0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-12&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/BCCRC.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Genetic and epigenetic inactivation of SESTRIN1 controls mTORC1 and response to EZH2 inhibition in follicular lymphoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28659443"/>
   <updated>2017-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28659443</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28659443&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follicular lymphoma (FL) is an incurable form of B cell lymphoma. Genomic studies have cataloged common genetic lesions in FL such as translocation t(14;18), frequent losses of chromosome 6q, and mutations in epigenetic regulators such as EZH2 Using a focused genetic screen, we identified SESTRIN1 as a relevant target of the 6q deletion and demonstrate tumor suppression by SESTRIN1 in vivo. Moreover, SESTRIN1 is a direct target of the lymphoma-specific EZH2 gain-of-function mutation (EZH2(Y641X) ). SESTRIN1 inactivation disrupts p53-mediated control of mammalian target of rapamycin complex 1 (mTORC1) and enables mRNA translation under genotoxic stress. SESTRIN1 loss represents an alternative to RRAGC mutations that maintain mTORC1 activity under nutrient starvation. The antitumor efficacy of pharmacological EZH2 inhibition depends on SESTRIN1, indicating that mTORC1 control is a critical function of EZH2 in lymphoma. Conversely, EZH2(Y641X) mutant lymphomas show increased sensitivity to RapaLink-1, a bifunctional mTOR inhibitor. Hence, SESTRIN1 contributes to the genetic and epigenetic control of mTORC1 in lymphoma and influences responses to targeted therapies.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Kronos: a workflow assembler for genome analytics and informatics.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28655203"/>
   <updated>2017-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28655203</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28655203&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field of next generation sequencing informatics has matured to a point where algorithmic advances in sequence alignment and individual feature detection methods have stabilized. Practical and robust implementation of complex analytical workflows (where such tools are structured into ‘best practices’ for automated analysis of NGS datasets) still requires significant programming investment and expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We present Kronos , a software platform for facilitating the development and execution of modular, auditable and distributable bioinformatics workflows. Kronos obviates the need for explicit coding of workflows by compiling a text configuration file into executable Python applications. Making analysis modules would still require programming The framework of each workflow includes a run manager to execute the encoded workflows locally (or on a cluster or cloud), parallelize tasks, and log all runtime events. Resulting workflows are highly modular and configurable by construction, facilitating flexible and extensible meta-applications which can be modified easily through configuration file editing. The workflows are fully encoded for ease of distribution and can be instantiated on external systems, a step towards reproducible research and comparative analyses. We introduce a framework for building Kronos components which function as shareable, modular nodes in Kronos workflows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kronos platform provides a standard framework for developers to implement custom tools, reuse existing tools, and contribute to the community at large. Kronos is shipped with both Docker and Amazon AWS machine images. It is free, open source and available through PyPI (Python Package Index) and https://github.com/jtaghiyar/kronos .&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Observing Clonal Dynamics Across Spatiotemporal Axes: A Prelude to Quantitative Fitness Models for Cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28630229"/>
   <updated>2017-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28630229</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28630229&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to accurately model evolutionary dynamics in cancer would allow for prediction of progression and response to therapy. As a prelude to quantitative understanding of evolutionary dynamics, researchers must gather observations of in vivo tumor evolution. High-throughput genome sequencing now provides the means to profile the mutational content of evolving tumor clones from patient biopsies. Together with the development of models of tumor evolution, reconstructing evolutionary histories of individual tumors generates hypotheses about the dynamics of evolution that produced the observed clones. In this review, we provide a brief overview of the concepts involved in predicting evolutionary histories, and provide a workflow based on bulk and targeted-genome sequencing. We then describe the application of this workflow to time series data obtained for transformed and progressed follicular lymphomas (FL), and contrast the observed evolutionary dynamics between these two subtypes. We next describe results from a spatial sampling study of high-grade serous (HGS) ovarian cancer, propose mechanisms of disease spread based on the observed clonal mixtures, and provide examples of diversification through subclonal acquisition of driver mutations and convergent evolution. Finally, we state implications of the techniques discussed in this review as a necessary but insufficient step on the path to predictive modelling of disease dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Jiarui Ding</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Jiarui-Ding"/>
   <updated>2017-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Jiarui-Ding</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>E-scape: interactive visualization of single-cell phylogenetics and cancer evolution.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28557980"/>
   <updated>2017-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28557980</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28557980&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Genomic consequences of aberrant DNA repair mechanisms stratify ovarian cancer histotypes.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28436987"/>
   <updated>2017-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28436987</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28436987&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We studied the whole-genome point mutation and structural variation patterns of 133 tumors (59 high-grade serous (HGSC), 35 clear cell (CCOC), 29 endometrioid (ENOC), and 10 adult granulosa cell (GCT)) as a substrate for class discovery in ovarian cancer. Ab initio clustering of integrated point mutation and structural variation signatures identified seven subgroups both between and within histotypes. Prevalence of foldback inversions identified a prognostically significant HGSC group associated with inferior survival. This finding was recapitulated in two independent cohorts (n = 576 cases), transcending BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation and gene expression features of HGSC. CCOC cancers grouped according to APOBEC deamination (26%) and age-related mutational signatures (40%). ENOCs were divided by cases with microsatellite instability (28%), with a distinct mismatch-repair mutation signature. Taken together, our work establishes the potency of the somatic genome, reflective of diverse DNA repair deficiencies, to stratify ovarian cancers into distinct biological strata within the major histotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Fong Chun Chan</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Fong-Chun-Chan"/>
   <updated>2017-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Fong-Chun-Chan</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Genetic profiling of MYC and BCL2 in diffuse large B-cell lymphoma determines cell-of-origin-specific clinical impact.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28351934"/>
   <updated>2017-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28351934</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28351934&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clinical significance of MYC and BCL2 genetic alterations in diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL), apart from translocations, has not been comprehensively investigated using high-resolution genetic assays. In this study, we profiled MYC and BCL2 genetic alterations using next-generation sequencing and high-resolution SNP array in 347 de novo DLBCL cases treated with R-CHOP (rituximab, cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone) at the British Columbia Cancer Agency. Cell-of-origin (COO) subtype was determined by Lymph2Cx digital gene expression profiling. We showed that the incidence of MYC/BCL2 genetic alterations and their clinical significance were largely dependent on COO subtypes. It is noteworthy that the presence of BCL2 gain/amplification is significantly associated with poor outcome in activated B-cell-like and BCL2 translocation with poor outcome in germinal center B-cell subtypes, respectively. Both have prognostic significance independent of MYC/BCL2 dual expression and the International Prognostic Index (IPI). Furthermore, the combination of BCL2 genetic alterations with IPI identifies markedly worse prognostic groups within individual COO subtypes. Thus, high-resolution genomic assays identify extremely poor prognostic groups within each COO subtype on the basis of BCL2 genetic status in this large, uniformly R-CHOP-treated population-based cohort of DLBCL. These results suggest COO subtype-specific biomarkers based on BCL2 genetic alterations can be used to risk-stratify patients with DLBCL treated with immunochemotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CDK12 regulates alternative last exon mRNA splicing and promotes breast cancer cell invasion.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28334900"/>
   <updated>2017-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28334900</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28334900&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDK12 (cyclin-dependent kinase 12) is a regulatory kinase with evolutionarily conserved roles in modulating transcription elongation. Recent tumor genome studies of breast and ovarian cancers highlighted recurrent CDK12 mutations, which have been shown to disrupt DNA repair in cell-based assays. In breast cancers, CDK12 is also frequently co-amplified with the HER2 (ERBB2) oncogene. The mechanisms underlying functions of CDK12 in general and in cancer remain poorly defined. Based on global analysis of mRNA transcripts in normal and breast cancer cell lines with and without CDK12 amplification, we demonstrate that CDK12 primarily regulates alternative last exon (ALE) splicing, a specialized subtype of alternative mRNA splicing, that is both gene- and cell type-specific. These are unusual properties for spliceosome regulatory factors, which typically regulate multiple forms of alternative splicing in a global manner. In breast cancer cells, regulation by CDK12 modulates ALE splicing of the DNA damage response activator ATM and a DNAJB6 isoform that influences cell invasion and tumorigenesis in xenografts. We found that there is a direct correlation between CDK12 levels, DNAJB6 isoform levels and the migration capacity and invasiveness of breast tumor cells. This suggests that CDK12 gene amplification can contribute to the pathogenesis of the cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Enhancing knowledge discovery from cancer genomics data with Galaxy.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28327945"/>
   <updated>2017-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28327945</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28327945&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field of cancer genomics has demonstrated the power of massively parallel sequencing techniques to inform on the genes and specific alterations that drive tumor onset and progression. Although large comprehensive sequence data sets continue to be made increasingly available, data analysis remains an ongoing challenge, particularly for laboratories lacking dedicated resources and bioinformatics expertise. To address this, we have produced a collection of Galaxy tools that represent many popular algorithms for detecting somatic genetic alterations from cancer genome and exome data. We developed new methods for parallelization of these tools within Galaxy to accelerate runtime and have demonstrated their usability and summarized their runtimes on multiple cloud service providers. Some tools represent extensions or refinement of existing toolkits to yield visualizations suited to cohort-wide cancer genomic analysis. For example, we present Oncocircos and Oncoprintplus, which generate data-rich summaries of exome-derived somatic mutation. Workflows that integrate these to achieve data integration and visualizations are demonstrated on a cohort of 96 diffuse large B-cell lymphomas and enabled the discovery of multiple candidate lymphoma-related genes. Our toolkit is available from our GitHub repository as Galaxy tool and dependency definitions and has been deployed using virtualization on multiple platforms including Docker.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ddClone: joint statistical inference of clonal populations from single cell and bulk tumour sequencing data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28249593"/>
   <updated>2017-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28249593</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28249593&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next-generation sequencing (NGS) of bulk tumour tissue can identify constituent cell populations in cancers and measure their abundance. This requires computational deconvolution of allelic counts from somatic mutations, which may be incapable of fully resolving the underlying population structure. Single cell sequencing (SCS) is a more direct method, although its replacement of NGS is impeded by technical noise and sampling limitations. We propose ddClone, which analytically integrates NGS and SCS data, leveraging their complementary attributes through joint statistical inference. We show on real and simulated datasets that ddClone produces more accurate results than can be achieved by either method alone.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CLK-dependent exon recognition and conjoined gene formation revealed with a novel small molecule inhibitor.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28232751"/>
   <updated>2017-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28232751</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28232751&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDC-like kinase phosphorylation of serine/arginine-rich proteins is central to RNA splicing reactions. Yet, the genomic network of CDC-like kinase-dependent RNA processing events remains poorly defined. Here, we explore the connectivity of genomic CDC-like kinase splicing functions by applying graduated, short-exposure, pharmacological CDC-like kinase inhibition using a novel small molecule (T3) with very high potency, selectivity, and cell-based stability. Using RNA-Seq, we define CDC-like kinase-responsive alternative splicing events, the large majority of which monotonically increase or decrease with increasing CDC-like kinase inhibition. We show that distinct RNA-binding motifs are associated with T3 response in skipped exons. Unexpectedly, we observe dose-dependent conjoined gene transcription, which is associated with motif enrichment in the last and second exons of upstream and downstream partners, respectively. siRNA knockdown of CLK2-associated genes significantly increases conjoined gene formation. Collectively, our results reveal an unexpected role for CDC-like kinase in conjoined gene formation, via regulation of 3’-end processing and associated splicing factors.The phosphorylation of serine/arginine-rich proteins by CDC-like kinase is a central regulatory mechanism for RNA splicing reactions. Here, the authors synthesize a novel small molecule CLK inhibitor and map CLK-responsive alternative splicing events and discover an effect on conjoined gene transcription.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CX-5461 is a DNA G-quadruplex stabilizer with selective lethality in BRCA1/2 deficient tumours.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28211448"/>
   <updated>2017-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28211448</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28211448&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;G-quadruplex DNAs form four-stranded helical structures and are proposed to play key roles in different cellular processes. Targeting G-quadruplex DNAs for cancer treatment is a very promising prospect. Here, we show that CX-5461 is a G-quadruplex stabilizer, with specific toxicity against BRCA deficiencies in cancer cells and polyclonal patient-derived xenograft models, including tumours resistant to PARP inhibition. Exposure to CX-5461, and its related drug CX-3543, blocks replication forks and induces ssDNA gaps or breaks. The BRCA and NHEJ pathways are required for the repair of CX-5461 and CX-3543-induced DNA damage and failure to do so leads to lethality. These data strengthen the concept of G4 targeting as a therapeutic approach, specifically for targeting HR and NHEJ deficient cancers and other tumours deficient for DNA damage repair. CX-5461 is now in advanced phase I clinical trial for patients with BRCA1/2 deficient tumours (Canadian trial, NCT02719977, opened May 2016).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Scalable whole-genome single-cell library preparation without preamplification.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/28068316"/>
   <updated>2017-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/28068316</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;28068316&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single-cell genomics is critical for understanding cellular heterogeneity in cancer, but existing library preparation methods are expensive, require sample preamplification and introduce coverage bias. Here we describe direct library preparation (DLP), a robust, scalable, and high-fidelity method that uses nanoliter-volume transposition reactions for single-cell whole-genome library preparation without preamplification. We examined 782 cells from cell lines and triple-negative breast xenograft tumors. Low-depth sequencing, compared with existing methods, revealed greater coverage uniformity and more reliable detection of copy-number alterations. Using phylogenetic analysis, we found minor xenograft subpopulations that were undetectable by bulk sequencing, as well as dynamic clonal expansion and diversification between passages. Merging single-cell genomes in silico, we generated ‘bulk-equivalent’ genomes with high depth and uniform coverage. Thus, low-depth sequencing of DLP libraries may provide an attractive replacement for conventional bulk sequencing methods, permitting analysis of copy number at the cell level and of other genomic variants at the population level.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Histological Transformation and Progression in Follicular Lymphoma: A Clonal Evolution Study.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/27959929"/>
   <updated>2016-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/27959929</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;27959929&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follicular lymphoma (FL) is an indolent, yet incurable B cell malignancy. A subset of patients experience an increased mortality rate driven by two distinct clinical end points: histological transformation and early progression after immunochemotherapy. The nature of tumor clonal dynamics leading to these clinical end points is poorly understood, and previously determined genetic alterations do not explain the majority of transformed cases or accurately predict early progressive disease. We contend that detailed knowledge of the expansion patterns of specific cell populations plus their associated mutations would provide insight into therapeutic strategies and disease biology over the time course of FL clinical histories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a combination of whole genome sequencing, targeted deep sequencing, and digital droplet PCR on matched diagnostic and relapse specimens, we deciphered the constituent clonal populations in 15 transformation cases and 6 progression cases, and measured the change in clonal population abundance over time. We observed widely divergent patterns of clonal dynamics in transformed cases relative to progressed cases. Transformation specimens were generally composed of clones that were rare or absent in diagnostic specimens, consistent with dramatic clonal expansions that came to dominate the transformation specimens. This pattern was independent of time to transformation and treatment modality. By contrast, early progression specimens were composed of clones that were already present in the diagnostic specimens and exhibited only moderate clonal dynamics, even in the presence of immunochemotherapy. Analysis of somatic mutations impacting 94 genes was undertaken in an extension cohort consisting of 395 samples from 277 patients in order to decipher disrupted biology in the two clinical end points. We found 12 genes that were more commonly mutated in transformed samples than in the preceding FL tumors, including TP53, B2M, CCND3, GNA13, S1PR2, and P2RY8. Moreover, ten genes were more commonly mutated in diagnostic specimens of patients with early progression, including TP53, BTG1, MKI67, and XBP1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our results illuminate contrasting modes of evolution shaping the clinical histories of transformation and progression. They have implications for interpretation of evolutionary dynamics in the context of treatment-induced selective pressures, and indicate that transformation and progression will require different clinical management strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Samantha Leung</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Samantha-Leung"/>
   <updated>2016-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Samantha-Leung</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Jamie Lim</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Jamie-Lim"/>
   <updated>2016-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Jamie-Lim</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Rebecca Asiimwe</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Rebecca-Asiimwe"/>
   <updated>2016-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Rebecca-Asiimwe</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Overexpression screens identify conserved dosage chromosome instability genes in yeast and human cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/27551064"/>
   <updated>2016-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/27551064</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;27551064&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somatic copy number amplification and gene overexpression are common features of many cancers. To determine the role of gene overexpression on chromosome instability (CIN), we performed genome-wide screens in the budding yeast for yeast genes that cause CIN when overexpressed, a phenotype we refer to as dosage CIN (dCIN), and identified 245 dCIN genes. This catalog of genes reveals human orthologs known to be recurrently overexpressed and/or amplified in tumors. We show that two genes, TDP1, a tyrosyl-DNA-phosphdiesterase, and TAF12, an RNA polymerase II TATA-box binding factor, cause CIN when overexpressed in human cells. Rhabdomyosarcoma lines with elevated human Tdp1 levels also exhibit CIN that can be partially rescued by siRNA-mediated knockdown of TDP1 Overexpression of dCIN genes represents a genetic vulnerability that could be leveraged for selective killing of cancer cells through targeting of an unlinked synthetic dosage lethal (SDL) partner. Using SDL screens in yeast, we identified a set of genes that when deleted specifically kill cells with high levels of Tdp1. One gene was the histone deacetylase RPD3, for which there are known inhibitors. Both HT1080 cells overexpressing hTDP1 and rhabdomyosarcoma cells with elevated levels of hTdp1 were more sensitive to histone deacetylase inhibitors valproic acid (VPA) and trichostatin A (TSA), recapitulating the SDL interaction in human cells and suggesting VPA and TSA as potential therapeutic agents for tumors with elevated levels of hTdp1. The catalog of dCIN genes presented here provides a candidate list to identify genes that cause CIN when overexpressed in cancer, which can then be leveraged through SDL to selectively target tumors.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Robust high-performance nanoliter-volume single-cell multiple displacement amplification on planar substrates.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/27412862"/>
   <updated>2016-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/27412862</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;27412862&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genomes of large numbers of single cells must be sequenced to further understanding of the biological significance of genomic heterogeneity in complex systems. Whole genome amplification (WGA) of single cells is generally the first step in such studies, but is prone to nonuniformity that can compromise genomic measurement accuracy. Despite recent advances, robust performance in high-throughput single-cell WGA remains elusive. Here, we introduce droplet multiple displacement amplification (MDA), a method that uses commercially available liquid dispensing to perform high-throughput single-cell MDA in nanoliter volumes. The performance of droplet MDA is characterized using a large dataset of 129 normal diploid cells, and is shown to exceed previously reported single-cell WGA methods in amplification uniformity, genome coverage, and/or robustness. We achieve up to 80% coverage of a single-cell genome at 5× sequencing depth, and demonstrate excellent single-nucleotide variant (SNV) detection using targeted sequencing of droplet MDA product to achieve a median allelic dropout of 15%, and using whole genome sequencing to achieve false and true positive rates of 9.66 × 10(-6) and 68.8%, respectively, in a G1-phase cell. We further show that droplet MDA allows for the detection of copy number variants (CNVs) as small as 30 kb in single cells of an ovarian cancer cell line and as small as 9 Mb in two high-grade serous ovarian cancer samples using only 0.02× depth. Droplet MDA provides an accessible and scalable method for performing robust and accurate CNV and SNV measurements on large numbers of single cells.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Andrew Roth</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Andrew-Roth"/>
   <updated>2016-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Andrew-Roth</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Clonal genotype and population structure inference from single-cell tumor sequencing.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/27183439"/>
   <updated>2016-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/27183439</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;27183439&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single-cell DNA sequencing has great potential to reveal the clonal genotypes and population structure of human cancers. However, single-cell data suffer from missing values and biased allelic counts as well as false genotype measurements owing to the sequencing of multiple cells. We describe the Single Cell Genotyper (https://bitbucket.org/aroth85/scg), an open-source software based on a statistical model coupled with a mean-field variational inference method, which can be used to address these problems and robustly infer clonal genotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Divergent modes of clonal spread and intraperitoneal mixing in high-grade serous ovarian cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/27182968"/>
   <updated>2016-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/27182968</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;27182968&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We performed phylogenetic analysis of high-grade serous ovarian cancers (68 samples from seven patients), identifying constituent clones and quantifying their relative abundances at multiple intraperitoneal sites. Through whole-genome and single-nucleus sequencing, we identified evolutionary features including mutation loss, convergence of the structural genome and temporal activation of mutational processes that patterned clonal progression. We then determined the precise clonal mixtures comprising each tumor sample. The majority of sites were clonally pure or composed of clones from a single phylogenetic clade. However, each patient contained at least one site composed of polyphyletic clones. Five patients exhibited monoclonal and unidirectional seeding from the ovary to intraperitoneal sites, and two patients demonstrated polyclonal spread and reseeding. Our findings indicate that at least two distinct modes of intraperitoneal spread operate in clonal dissemination and highlight the distribution of migratory potential over clonal populations comprising high-grade serous ovarian cancers.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The somatic mutation profiles of 2,433 breast cancers refines their genomic and transcriptomic landscapes.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/27161491"/>
   <updated>2016-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/27161491</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;27161491&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genomic landscape of breast cancer is complex, and inter- and intra-tumour heterogeneity are important challenges in treating the disease. In this study, we sequence 173 genes in 2,433 primary breast tumours that have copy number aberration (CNA), gene expression and long-term clinical follow-up data. We identify 40 mutation-driver (Mut-driver) genes, and determine associations between mutations, driver CNA profiles, clinical-pathological parameters and survival. We assess the clonal states of Mut-driver mutations, and estimate levels of intra-tumour heterogeneity using mutant-allele fractions. Associations between PIK3CA mutations and reduced survival are identified in three subgroups of ER-positive cancer (defined by amplification of 17q23, 11q13-14 or 8q24). High levels of intra-tumour heterogeneity are in general associated with a worse outcome, but highly aggressive tumours with 11q13-14 amplification have low levels of intra-tumour heterogeneity. These results emphasize the importance of genome-based stratification of breast cancer, and have important implications for designing therapeutic strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>densityCut: an efficient and versatile topological approach for automatic clustering of biological data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/27153661"/>
   <updated>2016-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/27153661</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;27153661&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many biological data processing problems can be formalized as clustering problems to partition data points into sensible and biologically interpretable groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article introduces densityCut, a novel density-based clustering algorithm, which is both time- and space-efficient and proceeds as follows: densityCut first roughly estimates the densities of data points from a K-nearest neighbour graph and then refines the densities via a random walk. A cluster consists of points falling into the basin of attraction of an estimated mode of the underlining density function. A post-processing step merges clusters and generates a hierarchical cluster tree. The number of clusters is selected from the most stable clustering in the hierarchical cluster tree. Experimental results on ten synthetic benchmark datasets and two microarray gene expression datasets demonstrate that densityCut performs better than state-of-the-art algorithms for clustering biological datasets. For applications, we focus on the recent cancer mutation clustering and single cell data analyses, namely to cluster variant allele frequencies of somatic mutations to reveal clonal architectures of individual tumours, to cluster single-cell gene expression data to uncover cell population compositions, and to cluster single-cell mass cytometry data to detect communities of cells of the same functional states or types. densityCut performs better than competing algorithms and is scalable to large datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;Data and the densityCut R package is available from https://bitbucket.org/jerry00/densitycut_dev&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;condon@cs.ubc.ca or sshah@bccrc.ca or jiaruid@cs.ubc.ca&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Identification of the epigenetic reader CBX2 as a potential drug target in advanced prostate cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26877821"/>
   <updated>2016-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26877821</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26877821&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While localized prostate cancer (PCa) can be effectively cured, metastatic disease inevitably progresses to a lethal state called castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC). Emerging evidence suggests that aberrant epigenetic repression by the polycomb group (PcG) complexes fuels PCa progression, providing novel therapeutic opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the search for potential epigenetic drivers of CRPC, we analyzed the molecular profile of PcG members in patient-derived xenografts and clinical samples. Overall, our results identify the PcG protein and methyl-lysine reader CBX2 as a potential therapeutic target in advanced PCa. We report that CBX2 was recurrently up-regulated in metastatic CRPC and that elevated CBX2 expression was correlated with poor clinical outcome in PCa cohorts. Furthermore, CBX2 depletion abrogated cell viability and induced caspase 3-mediated apoptosis in metastatic PCa cell lines. Mechanistically explaining this phenotype, microarray analysis in CBX2-depleted cells revealed that CBX2 controls the expression of many key regulators of cell proliferation and metastasis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken together, this study provides the first evidence that CBX2 inhibition induces cancer cell death, positioning CBX2 as an attractive drug target in lethal CRPC.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Synchronous Endometrial and Ovarian Carcinomas: Evidence of Clonality.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26832771"/>
   <updated>2016-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26832771</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26832771&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many women with ovarian endometrioid carcinoma present with concurrent endometrial carcinoma. Organ-confined and low-grade synchronous endometrial and ovarian tumors (SEOs) clinically behave as independent primary tumors rather than a single advanced-stage carcinoma. We used 18 SEOs to investigate the ancestral relationship between the endometrial and ovarian components. Based on both targeted and exome sequencing, 17 of 18 patient cases of simultaneous cancer of the endometrium and ovary from our series showed evidence of a clonal relationship, ie, primary tumor and metastasis. Eleven patient cases fulfilled clinicopathological criteria that would lead to classification as independent endometrial and ovarian primary carcinomas, including being of FIGO stage T1a/1A, with organ-restricted growth and without surface involvement; 10 of 11 of these cases showed evidence of clonality. Our observations suggest that the disseminating cells amongst SEOs are restricted to physically accessible and microenvironment-compatible sites yet remain indolent, without the capacity for further dissemination.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Divergent clonal selection dominates medulloblastoma at recurrence.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26760213"/>
   <updated>2016-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26760213</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26760213&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of targeted anti-cancer therapies through the study of cancer genomes is intended to increase survival rates and decrease treatment-related toxicity. We treated a transposon-driven, functional genomic mouse model of medulloblastoma with ‘humanized’ in vivo therapy (microneurosurgical tumour resection followed by multi-fractionated, image-guided radiotherapy). Genetic events in recurrent murine medulloblastoma exhibit a very poor overlap with those in matched murine diagnostic samples (&amp;lt;5%). Whole-genome sequencing of 33 pairs of human diagnostic and post-therapy medulloblastomas demonstrated substantial genetic divergence of the dominant clone after therapy (&amp;lt;12% diagnostic events were retained at recurrence). In both mice and humans, the dominant clone at recurrence arose through clonal selection of a pre-existing minor clone present at diagnosis. Targeted therapy is unlikely to be effective in the absence of the target, therefore our results offer a simple, proximal, and remediable explanation for the failure of prior clinical trials of targeted therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mirela Andronescu</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Mirela-Andronescu"/>
   <updated>2016-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Mirela-Andronescu</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am interested in designing computational algorithms to better understand biological changes in cancer. I am currently involved in designing probabilistic algorithms to find clones in very sparse single-cell DNA methylation data. I pursued my post-doc with Bill Noble in the Department of Genome Sciences, University of Washington, where I worked on statistical and computational methods to process and understand high-throughput pairwise chromatin interaction data. I received my Ph.D. and M.Sc. in Computer Science at the University of British Columbia, in the area of RNA secondary structure prediction and thermodynamic parameter estimation.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Daniel Lai</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Daniel-Lai"/>
   <updated>2015-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Daniel-Lai</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Multifocal clonal evolution characterized using circulating tumour DNA in a case of metastatic breast cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26530965"/>
   <updated>2015-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26530965</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26530965&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circulating tumour DNA analysis can be used to track tumour burden and analyse cancer genomes non-invasively but the extent to which it represents metastatic heterogeneity is unknown. Here we follow a patient with metastatic ER-positive and HER2-positive breast cancer receiving two lines of targeted therapy over 3 years. We characterize genomic architecture and infer clonal evolution in eight tumour biopsies and nine plasma samples collected over 1,193 days of clinical follow-up using exome and targeted amplicon sequencing. Mutation levels in the plasma samples reflect the clonal hierarchy inferred from sequencing of tumour biopsies. Serial changes in circulating levels of sub-clonal private mutations correlate with different treatment responses between metastatic sites. This comparison of biopsy and plasma samples in a single patient with metastatic breast cancer shows that circulating tumour DNA can allow real-time sampling of multifocal clonal evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Systematic analysis of somatic mutations impacting gene expression in 12 tumour types.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26436532"/>
   <updated>2015-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26436532</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26436532&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We present a novel hierarchical Bayes statistical model, xseq, to systematically quantify the impact of somatic mutations on expression profiles. We establish the theoretical framework and robust inference characteristics of the method using computational benchmarking. We then use xseq to analyse thousands of tumour data sets available through The Cancer Genome Atlas, to systematically quantify somatic mutations impacting expression profiles. We identify 30 novel cis-effect tumour suppressor gene candidates, enriched in loss-of-function mutations and biallelic inactivation. Analysis of trans-effects of mutations and copy number alterations with xseq identifies mutations in 150 genes impacting expression networks, with 89 novel predictions. We reveal two important novel characteristics of mutation impact on expression: (1) patients harbouring known driver mutations exhibit different downstream gene expression consequences; (2) expression patterns for some mutations are stable across tumour types. These results have critical implications for identification and interpretation of mutations with consequent impact on transcription in cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The genomic landscape of epithelioid sarcoma cell lines and tumours.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26365879"/>
   <updated>2015-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26365879</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26365879&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We carried out whole genome and transcriptome sequencing on four tumour/normal pairs of epithelioid sarcoma. These index cases were supplemented with whole transcriptome sequencing of three additional tumours and three cell lines. Unlike rhabdoid tumour (the other major group of SMARCB1-negative cancers), epithelioid sarcoma shows a complex genome with a higher mutational rate, comparable to that of ovarian carcinoma. Despite this mutational burden, SMARCB1 mutations remain the most frequently recurring event and are probably critical drivers of tumour formation. Several cases show heterozygous SMARCB1 mutations without inactivation of the second allele, and we explore this further in vitro. Finding CDKN2A deletions in our discovery cohort, we evaluated CDKN2A protein expression in a tissue microarray. Six out of 16 cases had lost CDKN2A in greater than or equal to 90% of cells, while the remaining cases had retained the protein. Expression analysis of epithelioid sarcoma cell lines by transcriptome sequencing shows a unique profile that does not cluster with any particular tissue type or with other SWI/SNF-aberrant lines. Evaluation of the levels of members of the SWI/SNF complex other than SMARCB1 revealed that these proteins are expressed as part of a residual complex, similarly to previously studied rhabdoid tumour lines. This residual SWI/SNF is susceptible to synthetic lethality and may therefore indicate a therapeutic opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Cell of origin of transformed follicular lymphoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26307535"/>
   <updated>2015-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26307535</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26307535&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follicular lymphoma (FL) is an indolent disease but transforms in 2% to 3% of patients per year into aggressive, large cell lymphoma, a critical event in the course of the disease associated with increased lymphoma-related mortality. Early transformation cannot be accurately predicted at the time of FL diagnosis and the biology of transformed FL (TFL) is poorly understood. Here, we assembled a cohort of 126 diagnostic FL specimens including 40 patients experiencing transformation (&amp;lt;5 years) and 86 patients not experiencing transformation for at least 5 years. In addition, we assembled an overlapping cohort of 155 TFL patients, including 114 cases for which paired samples were available, and assessed temporal changes of routinely available biomarkers, outcome after transformation, as well as molecular subtypes of TFL. We report that the expression of IRF4 is an independent predictor of early transformation (Hazard ratio, 13.3; P &amp;lt; .001). We also show that composite histology at the time of transformation predicts favorable prognosis. Moreover, applying the Lymph2Cx digital gene expression assay for diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) cell-of-origin determination to 110 patients with DLBCL-like TFL, we demonstrate that TFL is of the germinal-center B-cell-like subtype in the majority of cases (80%) but that a significant proportion of cases is of the activated B-cell-like (ABC) subtype (16%). These latter cases are commonly negative for BCL2 translocation and arise preferentially from BCL2 translocation-negative and/or IRF4-expressing FLs. Our study demonstrates the existence of molecular heterogeneity in TFL as well as its relationship to the antecedent FL.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Calvin Lefebvre</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Calvin-Lefebvre"/>
   <updated>2015-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Calvin-Lefebvre</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hereditary Diffuse Gastric Cancer Syndrome: CDH1 Mutations and Beyond.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26182300"/>
   <updated>2015-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26182300</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26182300&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-cadherin (CDH1) is a cancer predisposition gene mutated in families meeting clinically defined hereditary diffuse gastric cancer (HDGC). Reliable estimates of cancer risk and spectrum in germline mutation carriers are essential for management. For families without CDH1 mutations, genetic-based risk stratification has not been possible, resulting in limited clinical options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To derive accurate estimates of gastric and breast cancer risks in CDH1 mutation carriers and determine if germline mutations in other genes are associated with HDGC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing for CDH1 germline mutations was performed on 183 index cases meeting clinical criteria for HDGC. Penetrance was derived from 75 mutation-positive families from within this and other cohorts, comprising 3858 probands (353 with gastric cancer and 89 with breast cancer). Germline DNA from 144 HDGC probands lacking CDH1 mutations was screened using multiplexed targeted sequencing for 55 cancer-associated genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accurate estimates of gastric and breast cancer risks in CDH1 mutation carriers and the relative contribution of other cancer predisposition genes in familial gastric cancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirty-one distinct pathogenic CDH1 mutations (14 novel) were identified in 34 of 183 index cases (19%). By the age of 80 years, the cumulative incidence of gastric cancer was 70% (95% CI, 59%-80%) for males and 56% (95% CI, 44%-69%) for females, and the risk of breast cancer for females was 42% (95% CI, 23%-68%). In CDH1 mutation-negative index cases, candidate mutations were identified in 16 of 144 probands (11%), including mutations within genes of high and moderate penetrance: CTNNA1, BRCA2, STK11, SDHB, PRSS1, ATM, MSR1, and PALB2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the largest reported series of CDH1 mutation carriers, providing more precise estimates of age-associated risks of gastric and breast cancer that will improve counseling of unaffected carriers. In HDGC families lacking CDH1 mutations, testing of CTNNA1 and other tumor suppressor genes should be considered. Clinically defined HDGC families can harbor mutations in genes (ie, BRCA2) with different clinical ramifications from CDH1. Therefore, we propose that HDGC syndrome may be best defined by mutations in CDH1 and closely related genes, rather than through clinical criteria that capture families with heterogeneous susceptibility profiles.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using Somatic Mutations to Guide Treatment Decisions: Context Matters.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26181166"/>
   <updated>2015-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26181166</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26181166&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Spatial genomic heterogeneity within localized, multifocal prostate cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/26005866"/>
   <updated>2015-05-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/26005866</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26005866&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herein we provide a detailed molecular analysis of the spatial heterogeneity of clinically localized, multifocal prostate cancer to delineate new oncogenes or tumor suppressors. We initially determined the copy number aberration (CNA) profiles of 74 patients with index tumors of Gleason score 7. Of these, 5 patients were subjected to whole-genome sequencing using DNA quantities achievable in diagnostic biopsies, with detailed spatial sampling of 23 distinct tumor regions to assess intraprostatic heterogeneity in focal genomics. Multifocal tumors are highly heterogeneous for single-nucleotide variants (SNVs), CNAs and genomic rearrangements. We identified and validated a new recurrent amplification of MYCL, which is associated with TP53 deletion and unique profiles of DNA damage and transcriptional dysregulation. Moreover, we demonstrate divergent tumor evolution in multifocal cancer and, in some cases, tumors of independent clonal origin. These data represent the first systematic relation of intraprostatic genomic heterogeneity to predicted clinical outcome and inform the development of novel biomarkers that reflect individual prognosis.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Allen Zhang</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Allen-Zhang"/>
   <updated>2015-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Allen-Zhang</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Cis-regulatory somatic mutations and gene-expression alteration in B-cell lymphomas.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/25903198"/>
   <updated>2015-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/25903198</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25903198&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rapid increase of whole-genome sequencing of human cancers, an important opportunity to analyze and characterize somatic mutations lying within cis-regulatory regions has emerged. A focus on protein-coding regions to identify nonsense or missense mutations disruptive to protein structure and/or function has led to important insights; however, the impact on gene expression of mutations lying within cis-regulatory regions remains under-explored. We analyzed somatic mutations from 84 matched tumor-normal whole genomes from B-cell lymphomas with accompanying gene expression measurements to elucidate the extent to which these cancers are disrupted by cis-regulatory mutations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We characterize mutations overlapping a high quality set of well-annotated transcription factor binding sites (TFBSs), covering a similar portion of the genome as protein-coding exons. Our results indicate that cis-regulatory mutations overlapping predicted TFBSs are enriched in promoter regions of genes involved in apoptosis or growth/proliferation. By integrating gene expression data with mutation data, our computational approach culminates with identification of cis-regulatory mutations most likely to participate in dysregulation of the gene expression program. The impact can be measured along with protein-coding mutations to highlight key mutations disrupting gene expression and pathways in cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our study yields specific genes with disrupted expression triggered by genomic mutations in either the coding or the regulatory space. It implies that mutated regulatory components of the genome contribute substantially to cancer pathways. Our analyses demonstrate that identifying genomically altered cis-regulatory elements coupled with analysis of gene expression data will augment biological interpretation of mutational landscapes of cancers.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Recurrent genomic rearrangements in primary testicular lymphoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/25712539"/>
   <updated>2015-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/25712539</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25712539&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primary testicular diffuse large B cell lymphoma (PTL) is an aggressive malignancy that occurs in the immune-privileged anatomical site of the testis. We have previously shown that structural genomic rearrangements involving the MHC class II transactivator CIITA and programmed death ligands (PDLs) 1 and 2 are frequent across multiple B cell lymphoma entities. Specifically in PTL, we found rearrangements in the PDL locus by fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH). However, breakpoint anatomy and rearrangement partners were undetermined, while CIITA rearrangements had not been reported previously in PTL. Here, we performed bacterial artificial chromosome capture sequencing on three archival, formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tissue biopsies, interrogating 20 known rearrangement hotspots in B cell lymphomas. We report novel CIITA, FOXP1 and PDL rearrangements involving IGHG4, FLJ45248, RFX3, SMARCA2 and SNX29. Moreover, we present immunohistochemistry data supporting the association between PDL rearrangements and increased protein expression. Finally, using FISH, we show that CIITA (8/82; 10%) and FOXP1 (5/74; 7%) rearrangements are recurrent in PTL. In summary, we describe rearrangement frequencies and novel rearrangement partners of the CIITA, FOXP1 and PDL loci at base-pair resolution in a rare, aggressive lymphoma. Our data suggest immune-checkpoint inhibitor therapy as a promising intervention for PTL patients harbouring PDL rearrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Multifocal endometriotic lesions associated with cancer are clonal and carry a high mutation burden.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/25692284"/>
   <updated>2015-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/25692284</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25692284&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Endometriosis is a significant risk factor for clear cell and endometrioid ovarian cancers and is often found contiguous with these cancers. Using whole-genome shotgun sequencing of seven clear cell ovarian carcinomas (CCC) and targeted sequencing in synchronous endometriosis, we have investigated how this carcinoma may evolve from endometriosis. In every case we observed multiple tumour-associated somatic mutations in at least one concurrent endometriotic lesion. ARID1A and PIK3CA mutations appeared consistently in concurrent endometriosis when present in the primary CCC. In several cases, one or more endometriotic lesions carried the near-complete complement of somatic mutations present in the index CCC tumour. Ancestral mutations were detected in both tumour-adjacent and -distant endometriotic lesions, regardless of any cytological atypia. These findings provide objective evidence that multifocal benign endometriotic lesions are clonally related and that CCCs arising in these patients progress from endometriotic lesions that may already carry sufficient cancer-associated mutations to be considered neoplasms themselves, albeit with low malignant potential. We speculate that genomically distinct classes of endometriosis exist and that ovarian endometriosis with high mutational burden represents one class at high risk for malignant transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>DNA barcoding reveals diverse growth kinetics of human breast tumour subclones in serially passaged xenografts.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/25532760"/>
   <updated>2014-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/25532760</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25532760&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genomic and phenotypic analyses indicate extensive intra- as well as intertumoral heterogeneity in primary human malignant cell populations despite their clonal origin. Cellular DNA barcoding offers a powerful and unbiased alternative to track the number and size of multiple subclones within a single human tumour xenograft and their response to continued in vivo passaging. Using this approach we find clone-initiating cell frequencies that vary from ~1/10 to ~1/10,000 cells transplanted for two human breast cancer cell lines and breast cancer xenografts derived from three different patients. For the cell lines, these frequencies are negatively affected in transplants of more than 20,000 cells. Serial transplants reveal five clonal growth patterns (unchanging, expanding, diminishing, fluctuating or of delayed onset), whose predominance is highly variable both between and within original samples. This study thus demonstrates the high growth potential and diverse growth properties of xenografted human breast cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Intratumoral heterogeneity in a minority of ovarian low-grade serous carcinomas.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/25523272"/>
   <updated>2014-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/25523272</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25523272&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovarian low-grade serous carcinoma (LGSC) has fewer mutations than ovarian high-grade serous carcinoma (HGSC) and a less aggressive clinical course. However, an overwhelming majority of LGSC patients do not respond to conventional chemotherapy resulting in a poor long-term prognosis comparable to women diagnosed with HGSC. KRAS and BRAF mutations are common in LGSC, leading to clinical trials targeting the MAPK pathway. We assessed the stability of targetable somatic mutations over space and/or time in LGSC, with a view to inform stratified treatment strategies and clinical trial design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eleven LGSC cases with primary and recurrent paired samples were identified (stage IIB-IV). Tumor DNA was isolated from 1-4 formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded tumor blocks from both the primary and recurrence (n = 37 tumor and n = 7 normal samples). Mutational analysis was performed using the Ion Torrent AmpliSeqTM Cancer Panel, with targeted validation using Fluidigm-MiSeq, Sanger sequencing and/or Raindance Raindrop digital PCR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KRAS (3/11), BRAF (2/11) and/or NRAS (1/11) mutations were identified in five unique cases. A novel, non-synonymous mutation in SMAD4 was observed in one case. No somatic mutations were detected in the remaining six cases. In two cases with a single matched primary and recurrent sample, two KRAS hotspot mutations (G12V, G12R) were both stable over time. In three cases with multiple samplings from both the primary and recurrent surgery some mutations (NRAS Q61R, BRAF V600E, SMAD4 R361G) were stable across all samples, while others (KRAS G12V, BRAF G469V) were unstable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the majority of cases with detectable somatic mutations showed mutational stability over space and time while one of five cases showed both temporal and spatial mutational instability in presumed drivers of disease. Investigation of additional cases is required to confirm whether mutational heterogeneity in a minority of LGSC is a general phenomenon that should be factored into the design of clinical trials and stratified treatment for this patient population.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dynamics of genomic clones in breast cancer patient xenografts at single-cell resolution.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/25470049"/>
   <updated>2014-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/25470049</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25470049&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human cancers, including breast cancers, comprise clones differing in mutation content. Clones evolve dynamically in space and time following principles of Darwinian evolution, underpinning important emergent features such as drug resistance and metastasis. Human breast cancer xenoengraftment is used as a means of capturing and studying tumour biology, and breast tumour xenografts are generally assumed to be reasonable models of the originating tumours. However, the consequences and reproducibility of engraftment and propagation on the genomic clonal architecture of tumours have not been systematically examined at single-cell resolution. Here we show, using deep-genome and single-cell sequencing methods, the clonal dynamics of initial engraftment and subsequent serial propagation of primary and metastatic human breast cancers in immunodeficient mice. In all 15 cases examined, clonal selection on engraftment was observed in both primary and metastatic breast tumours, varying in degree from extreme selective engraftment of minor (&amp;lt;5% of starting population) clones to moderate, polyclonal engraftment. Furthermore, ongoing clonal dynamics during serial passaging is a feature of tumours experiencing modest initial selection. Through single-cell sequencing, we show that major mutation clusters estimated from tumour population sequencing relate predictably to the most abundant clonal genotypes, even in clonally complex and rapidly evolving cases. Finally, we show that similar clonal expansion patterns can emerge in independent grafts of the same starting tumour population, indicating that genomic aberrations can be reproducible determinants of evolutionary trajectories. Our results show that measurement of genomically defined clonal population dynamics will be highly informative for functional studies using patient-derived breast cancer xenoengraftment.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>An RCOR1 loss-associated gene expression signature identifies a prognostically significant DLBCL subgroup.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/25395426"/>
   <updated>2014-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/25395426</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25395426&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective treatment of diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) is plagued by heterogeneous responses to standard therapy, and molecular mechanisms underlying unfavorable outcomes in lymphoma patients remain elusive. Here, we profiled 148 genomes with 91 matching transcriptomes in a DLBCL cohort treated with rituximab plus cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisolone (R-CHOP) to uncover molecular subgroups linked to treatment failure. Systematic integration of high-resolution genotyping arrays and RNA sequencing data revealed novel deletions in RCOR1 to be associated with unfavorable progression-free survival (P = .001). Integration of expression data from the clinical samples with data from RCOR1 knockdowns in the lymphoma cell lines KM-H2 and Raji yielded an RCOR1 loss-associated gene signature comprising 233 genes. This signature identified a subgroup of patients with unfavorable overall survival (P = .023). The prognostic significance of the 233-gene signature for overall survival was reproduced in an independent cohort comprising 195 R-CHOP-treated patients (P = .039). Additionally, we discovered that within the International Prognostic Index low-risk group, the gene signature provides additional prognostic value that was independent of the cell-of-origin phenotype. We present a novel and reproducible molecular subgroup of DLBCL that impacts risk-stratification of R-CHOP-treated DLBCL patients and reveals a possible new avenue for therapeutic intervention strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A tumor DNA complex aberration index is an independent predictor of survival in breast and ovarian cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/25169931"/>
   <updated>2014-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/25169931</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25169931&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complex focal chromosomal rearrangements in cancer genomes, also called “firestorms”, can be scored from DNA copy number data. The complex arm-wise aberration index (CAAI) is a score that captures DNA copy number alterations that appear as focal complex events in tumors, and has potential prognostic value in breast cancer. This study aimed to validate this DNA-based prognostic index in breast cancer and test for the first time its potential prognostic value in ovarian cancer. Copy number alteration (CNA) data from 1950 breast carcinomas (METABRIC cohort) and 508 high-grade serous ovarian carcinomas (TCGA dataset) were analyzed. Cases were classified as CAAI positive if at least one complex focal event was scored. Complex alterations were frequently localized on chromosome 8p (n = 159), 17q (n = 176) and 11q (n = 251). CAAI events on 11q were most frequent in estrogen receptor positive (ER+) cases and on 17q in estrogen receptor negative (ER-) cases. We found only a modest correlation between CAAI and the overall rate of genomic instability (GII) and number of breakpoints (r = 0.27 and r = 0.42, p &amp;lt; 0.001). Breast cancer specific survival (BCSS), overall survival (OS) and ovarian cancer progression free survival (PFS) were used as clinical end points in Cox proportional hazard model survival analyses. CAAI positive breast cancers (43%) had higher mortality: hazard ratio (HR) of 1.94 (95%CI, 1.62-2.32) for BCSS, and of 1.49 (95%CI, 1.30-1.71) for OS. Representations of the 70-gene and the 21-gene predictors were compared with CAAI in multivariable models and CAAI was independently significant with a Cox adjusted HR of 1.56 (95%CI, 1.23-1.99) for ER+ and 1.55 (95%CI, 1.11-2.18) for ER- disease. None of the expression-based predictors were prognostic in the ER- subset. We found that a model including CAAI and the two expression-based prognostic signatures outperformed a model including the 21-gene and 70-gene signatures but excluding CAAI. Inclusion of CAAI in the clinical prognostication tool PREDICT significantly improved its performance. CAAI positive ovarian cancers (52%) also had worse prognosis: HRs of 1.3 (95%CI, 1.1-1.7) for PFS and 1.3 (95%CI, 1.1-1.6) for OS. This study validates CAAI as an independent predictor of survival in both ER+ and ER- breast cancer and reveals a significant prognostic value for CAAI in high-grade serous ovarian cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gavin Ha</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Gavin-Ha"/>
   <updated>2014-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Gavin-Ha</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>TITAN: inference of copy number architectures in clonal cell populations from tumor whole-genome sequence data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/25060187"/>
   <updated>2014-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/25060187</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25060187&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evolution of cancer genomes within a single tumor creates mixed cell populations with divergent somatic mutational landscapes. Inference of tumor subpopulations has been disproportionately focused on the assessment of somatic point mutations, whereas computational methods targeting evolutionary dynamics of copy number alterations (CNA) and loss of heterozygosity (LOH) in whole-genome sequencing data remain underdeveloped. We present a novel probabilistic model, TITAN, to infer CNA and LOH events while accounting for mixtures of cell populations, thereby estimating the proportion of cells harboring each event. We evaluate TITAN on idealized mixtures, simulating clonal populations from whole-genome sequences taken from genomically heterogeneous ovarian tumor sites collected from the same patient. In addition, we show in 23 whole genomes of breast tumors that the inference of CNA and LOH using TITAN critically informs population structure and the nature of the evolving cancer genome. Finally, we experimentally validated subclonal predictions using fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) and single-cell sequencing from an ovarian cancer patient sample, thereby recapitulating the key modeling assumptions of TITAN.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mutational context and diverse clonal development in early and late bladder cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/24835989"/>
   <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/24835989</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;24835989&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bladder cancer (or urothelial cell carcinoma [UCC]) is characterized by field disease (malignant alterations in surrounding mucosa) and frequent recurrences. Whole-genome, exome, and transcriptome sequencing of 38 tumors, including four metachronous tumor pairs and 20 superficial tumors, identified an APOBEC mutational signature in one-third. This was biased toward the sense strand, correlated with mean expression level, and clustered near breakpoints. A&amp;gt;G mutations were up to eight times more frequent on the sense strand (p&amp;lt;0.002) in [ACG]AT contexts. The patient-specific APOBEC signature was negatively correlated to repair-gene expression and was not related to clinicopathological parameters. Mutations in gene families and single genes were related to tumor stage, and expression of chromatin modifiers correlated with survival. Evolutionary and subclonal analyses of early/late tumor pairs showed a unitary origin, and discrete tumor clones contained mutated cancer genes. The ancestral clones contained Pik3ca/Kdm6a mutations and may reflect the field-disease mutations shared among later tumors.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Tyler Funnell</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Tyler-Funnell"/>
   <updated>2014-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Tyler-Funnell</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Small cell carcinoma of the ovary, hypercalcemic type, displays frequent inactivating germline and somatic mutations in SMARCA4.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/24658001"/>
   <updated>2014-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/24658001</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;24658001&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small cell carcinoma of the ovary of hypercalcemic type (SCCOHT) is an extremely rare, aggressive cancer affecting children and young women. We identified germline and somatic inactivating mutations in the SWI/SNF chromatin-remodeling gene SMARCA4 in 75% (9/12) of SCCOHT cases in addition to SMARCA4 protein loss in 82% (14/17) of SCCOHT tumors but in only 0.4% (2/485) of other primary ovarian tumors. These data implicate SMARCA4 in SCCOHT oncogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>PyClone: statistical inference of clonal population structure in cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/24633410"/>
   <updated>2014-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/24633410</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;24633410&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We introduce PyClone, a statistical model for inference of clonal population structures in cancers. PyClone is a Bayesian clustering method for grouping sets of deeply sequenced somatic mutations into putative clonal clusters while estimating their cellular prevalences and accounting for allelic imbalances introduced by segmental copy-number changes and normal-cell contamination. Single-cell sequencing validation demonstrates PyClone’s accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Recurrent somatic mutations of PTPN1 in primary mediastinal B cell lymphoma and Hodgkin lymphoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/24531327"/>
   <updated>2014-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/24531327</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;24531327&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classical Hodgkin lymphoma and primary mediastinal B cell lymphoma (PMBCL) are related lymphomas sharing pathological, molecular and clinical characteristics. Here we discovered by whole-genome and whole-transcriptome sequencing recurrent somatic coding-sequence mutations in the PTPN1 gene. Mutations were found in 6 of 30 (20%) Hodgkin lymphoma cases, in 6 of 9 (67%) Hodgkin lymphoma-derived cell lines, in 17 of 77 (22%) PMBCL cases and in 1 of 3 (33%) PMBCL-derived cell lines, consisting of nonsense, missense and frameshift mutations. We demonstrate that PTPN1 mutations lead to reduced phosphatase activity and increased phosphorylation of JAK-STAT pathway members. Moreover, silencing of PTPN1 by RNA interference in Hodgkin lymphoma cell line KM-H2 resulted in hyperphosphorylation and overexpression of downstream oncogenic targets. Our data establish PTPN1 mutations as new drivers in lymphomagenesis.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Genomic rearrangements involving programmed death ligands are recurrent in primary mediastinal large B-cell lymphoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/24497532"/>
   <updated>2014-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/24497532</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;24497532&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pathogenesis of primary mediastinal large B-cell lymphoma (PMBCL) is incompletely understood. Recently, specific genotypic and phenotypic features have been linked to tumor cell immune escape mechanisms in PMBCL. We studied 571 B-cell lymphomas with a focus on PMBCL. Using fluorescence in situ hybridization here, we report that the programmed death ligand (PDL) locus (9p24.1) is frequently and specifically rearranged in PMBCL (20%) as compared with diffuse large B-cell lymphoma, follicular lymphoma, and Hodgkin lymphoma. Rearrangement was significantly correlated with overexpression of PDL transcripts. Utilizing high-throughput sequencing techniques, we characterized novel translocations and chimeric fusion transcripts involving PDLs at base-pair resolution. Our data suggest that recurrent genomic rearrangement events underlie an immune privilege phenotype in a subset of B-cell lymphomas.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A robust hidden semi-Markov model with application to aCGH data processing.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/24400520"/>
   <updated>2014-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/24400520</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;24400520&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hidden semi-Markov models are effective at modelling sequences with succession of homogenous zones by choosing appropriate state duration distributions. To compensate for model mis-specification and provide protection against outliers, we design a robust hidden semi-Markov model with Student’s t mixture models as the emission distributions. The proposed approach is used to model array based comparative genomic hybridization data. Experiments conducted on the benchmark data from the Coriell cell lines, and glioblastoma multiforme data illustrate the reliability of the technique.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Diljot Grewal</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Diljot-Grewal"/>
   <updated>2014-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Diljot-Grewal</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Fatemeh Dorri</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Fatemeh-Dorri"/>
   <updated>2013-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Fatemeh-Dorri</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Type-specific cell line models for type-specific ovarian cancer research.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/24023729"/>
   <updated>2013-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/24023729</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;24023729&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OVARIAN CARCINOMAS CONSIST OF AT LEAST FIVE DISTINCT DISEASES: high-grade serous, low-grade serous, clear cell, endometrioid, and mucinous. Biomarker and molecular characterization may represent a more biologically relevant basis for grouping and treating this family of tumors, rather than site of origin. Molecular characteristics have become the new standard for clinical pathology, however development of tailored type-specific therapies is hampered by a failure of basic research to recognize that model systems used to study these diseases must also be stratified. Unrelated model systems do offer value for study of biochemical processes but specific cellular context needs to be applied to assess relevant therapeutic strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have focused on the identification of clear cell carcinoma cell line models. A panel of 32 “ovarian cancer” cell lines has been classified into histotypes using a combination of mutation profiles, IHC mutation-surrogates, and a validated immunohistochemical model. All cell lines were identity verified using STR analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many described ovarian clear cell lines have characteristic mutations (including ARID1A and PIK3CA) and an overall molecular/immuno-profile typical of primary tumors. Mutations in TP53 were present in the majority of high-grade serous cell lines. Advanced genomic analysis of bona-fide clear cell carcinoma cell lines also support copy number changes in typical biomarkers such at MET and HNF1B and a lack of any recurrent expressed re-arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with primary ovarian tumors, mutation status of cancer genes like ARID1A and TP53 and a general immuno-profile serve well for establishing histotype of ovarian cancer cell We describe specific biomarkers and molecular features to re-classify generic “ovarian carcinoma” cell lines into type specific categories. Our data supports the use of prototype clear cell lines, such as TOV21G and JHOC-5, and questions the use of SKOV3 and A2780 as models of high-grade serous carcinoma.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sohrab Salehi</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Sohrab-Salehi"/>
   <updated>2013-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Sohrab-Salehi</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Distinct evolutionary trajectories of primary high-grade serous ovarian cancers revealed through spatial mutational profiling.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/23780408"/>
   <updated>2013-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/23780408</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;23780408&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High-grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSC) is characterized by poor outcome, often attributed to the emergence of treatment-resistant subclones. We sought to measure the degree of genomic diversity within primary, untreated HGSCs to examine the natural state of tumour evolution prior to therapy. We performed exome sequencing, copy number analysis, targeted amplicon deep sequencing and gene expression profiling on 31 spatially and temporally separated HGSC tumour specimens (six patients), including ovarian masses, distant metastases and fallopian tube lesions. We found widespread intratumoural variation in mutation, copy number and gene expression profiles, with key driver alterations in genes present in only a subset of samples (eg PIK3CA, CTNNB1, NF1). On average, only 51.5% of mutations were present in every sample of a given case (range 10.2-91.4%), with TP53 as the only somatic mutation consistently present in all samples. Complex segmental aneuploidies, such as whole-genome doubling, were present in a subset of samples from the same individual, with divergent copy number changes segregating independently of point mutation acquisition. Reconstruction of evolutionary histories showed one patient with mixed HGSC and endometrioid histology, with common aetiologic origin in the fallopian tube and subsequent selection of different driver mutations in the histologically distinct samples. In this patient, we observed mixed cell populations in the early fallopian tube lesion, indicating that diversity arises at early stages of tumourigenesis. Our results revealed that HGSCs exhibit highly individual evolutionary trajectories and diverse genomic tapestries prior to therapy, exposing an essential biological characteristic to inform future design of personalized therapeutic solutions and investigation of drug-resistance mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ovarian and endometrial endometrioid carcinomas have distinct CTNNB1 and PTEN mutation profiles.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/23765252"/>
   <updated>2013-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/23765252</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;23765252&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovarian endometrioid carcinomas and endometrial endometrioid carcinomas share many histological and molecular alterations. These similarities are likely due to a common endometrial epithelial precursor cell of origin, with most ovarian endometrioid carcinomas arising from endometriosis. To directly compare the mutation profiles of two morphologically similar tumor types, endometrial endometrioid carcinomas (n=307) and ovarian endometrioid carcinomas (n=33), we performed select exon capture sequencing on a panel of genes: ARID1A, PTEN, PIK3CA, KRAS, CTNNB1, PPP2R1A, TP53. We found that PTEN mutations are more frequent in low-grade endometrial endometrioid carcinomas (67%) compared with low-grade ovarian endometrioid carcinomas (17%) (P&amp;lt;0.0001). By contrast, CTNNB1 mutations are significantly different in low-grade ovarian endometrioid carcinomas (53%) compared with low-grade endometrial endometrioid carcinomas (28%) (P&amp;lt;0.0057). This difference in CTNNB1 mutation frequency may be reflective of the distinct microenvironments; the epithelial cells lining an endometriotic cyst within the ovary are exposed to a highly oxidative environment that promotes tumorigenesis. Understanding the distinct mutation patterns found in the PI3K and Wnt pathways of ovarian and endometrial endometrioid carcinomas may provide future opportunities for stratifying patients for targeted therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mutational and structural analysis of diffuse large B-cell lymphoma using whole-genome sequencing.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/23699601"/>
   <updated>2013-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/23699601</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;23699601&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) is a genetically heterogeneous cancer composed of at least 2 molecular subtypes that differ in gene expression and distribution of mutations. Recently, application of genome/exome sequencing and RNA-seq to DLBCL has revealed numerous genes that are recurrent targets of somatic point mutation in this disease. Here we provide a whole-genome-sequencing-based perspective of DLBCL mutational complexity by characterizing 40 de novo DLBCL cases and 13 DLBCL cell lines and combining these data with DNA copy number analysis and RNA-seq from an extended cohort of 96 cases. Our analysis identified widespread genomic rearrangements including evidence for chromothripsis as well as the presence of known and novel fusion transcripts. We uncovered new gene targets of recurrent somatic point mutations and genes that are targeted by focal somatic deletions in this disease. We highlight the recurrence of germinal center B-cell-restricted mutations affecting genes that encode the S1P receptor and 2 small GTPases (GNA13 and GNAI2) that together converge on regulation of B-cell homing. We further analyzed our data to approximate the relative temporal order in which some recurrent mutations were acquired and demonstrate that ongoing acquisition of mutations and intratumoral clonal heterogeneity are common features of DLBCL. This study further improves our understanding of the processes and pathways involved in lymphomagenesis, and some of the pathways mutated here may indicate new avenues for therapeutic intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Distinguishing somatic and germline copy number events in cancer patient DNA hybridized to whole-genome SNP genotyping arrays.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/23412801"/>
   <updated>2013-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/23412801</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;23412801&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chromosomal aneuploidy and segmental copy number changes are common genomic aberrations in -cancer. Copy number alterations (CNAs) arise from deletions, insertions, or duplications resulting in -chromosomal aberrations and aneuploidy. Genomes of normal cells also exhibit variable copy number called germline copy number variants (CNVs). CNVs in the general population tend to confound interpretation of predictions when attempting to extract relevant driver somatic events in cancer. In large studies of CNAs in cancer patients, it becomes necessary to accurately identify and separate CNAs and CNVs so as to prioritize candidate tumor suppressors and oncogenes. We have developed a probabilistic approach, HMM-Dosage, for segmenting and distinguishing CNAs and CNVs as separate, discrete events in cancer SNP genotyping array data. We outline the steps and computer code for the analysis of whole-genome cancer DNA hybridized to SNP genotyping arrays, focusing on distinguishing somatic CNA and germline CNVs, and describe the combined approach of HMM-Dosage for probabilistic inference and classification of somatic and germline copy number changes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>DriverNet: uncovering the impact of somatic driver mutations on transcriptional networks in cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/23383675"/>
   <updated>2013-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/23383675</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;23383675&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simultaneous interrogation of tumor genomes and transcriptomes is underway in unprecedented global efforts. Yet, despite the essential need to separate driver mutations modulating gene expression networks from transcriptionally inert passenger mutations, robust computational methods to ascertain the impact of individual mutations on transcriptional networks are underdeveloped. We introduce a novel computational framework, DriverNet, to identify likely driver mutations by virtue of their effect on mRNA expression networks. Application to four cancer datasets reveals the prevalence of rare candidate driver mutations associated with disrupted transcriptional networks and a simultaneous modulation of oncogenic and metabolic networks, induced by copy number co-modification of adjacent oncogenic and metabolic drivers. DriverNet is available on Bioconductor or at http://compbio.bccrc.ca/software/drivernet/.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gholamreza Haffari</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Gholamreza-Haffari"/>
   <updated>2013-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Gholamreza-Haffari</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>iReckon: simultaneous isoform discovery and abundance estimation from RNA-seq data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/23204306"/>
   <updated>2012-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/23204306</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;23204306&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High-throughput RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) promises to revolutionize our understanding of genes and their role in human disease by characterizing the RNA content of tissues and cells. The realization of this promise, however, is conditional on the development of effective computational methods for the identification and quantification of transcripts from incomplete and noisy data. In this article, we introduce iReckon, a method for simultaneous determination of the isoforms and estimation of their abundances. Our probabilistic approach incorporates multiple biological and technical phenomena, including novel isoforms, intron retention, unspliced pre-mRNA, PCR amplification biases, and multimapped reads. iReckon utilizes regularized expectation-maximization to accurately estimate the abundances of known and novel isoforms. Our results on simulated and real data demonstrate a superior ability to discover novel isoforms with a significantly reduced number of false-positive predictions, and our abundance accuracy prediction outmatches that of other state-of-the-art tools. Furthermore, we have applied iReckon to two cancer transcriptome data sets, a triple-negative breast cancer patient sample and the MCF7 breast cancer cell line, and show that iReckon is able to reconstruct the complex splicing changes that were not previously identified. QT-PCR validations of the isoforms detected in the MCF7 cell line confirmed all of iReckon’s predictions and also showed strong agreement (r(2) = 0.94) with the predicted abundances.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gene expression profiling of microdissected Hodgkin Reed-Sternberg cells correlates with treatment outcome in classical Hodgkin lymphoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22955918"/>
   <updated>2012-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22955918</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22955918&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In classical Hodgkin lymphoma (CHL), 20%-30% of patients experience relapse or progressive disease after initial treatment. The pathogenesis and biology of treatment failure are still poorly understood, in part because the molecular phenotype of the rare malignant Hodgkin Reed-Sternberg (HRS) cells is difficult to study. Here we examined microdissected HRS cells from 29 CHL patients and 5 CHL-derived cell lines by gene expression profiling. We found significant overlap of HL-specific gene expression in primary HRS cells and HL cell lines, but also differences, including surface receptor signaling pathways. Using integrative analysis tools, we identified target genes with expression levels that significantly correlated with genomic copy-number changes in primary HRS cells. Furthermore, we found a macrophage-like signature in HRS cells that significantly correlated with treatment failure. CSF1R is a representative of this signature, and its expression was significantly associated with progression-free and overall survival in an independent set of 132 patients assessed by mRNA in situ hybridization. A combined score of CSF1R in situ hybridization and CD68 immunohistochemistry was an independent predictor for progression-free survival in multivariate analysis. In summary, our data reveal novel insights into the pathobiology of treatment failure and suggest CSF1R as a drug target of at-risk CHL.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mutation discovery in regions of segmental cancer genome amplifications with CoNAn-SNV: a mixture model for next generation sequencing of tumors.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22916110"/>
   <updated>2012-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22916110</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22916110&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next generation sequencing has now enabled a cost-effective enumeration of the full mutational complement of a tumor genome-in particular single nucleotide variants (SNVs). Most current computational and statistical models for analyzing next generation sequencing data, however, do not account for cancer-specific biological properties, including somatic segmental copy number alterations (CNAs)-which require special treatment of the data. Here we present CoNAn-SNV (Copy Number Annotated SNV): a novel algorithm for the inference of single nucleotide variants (SNVs) that overlap copy number alterations. The method is based on modelling the notion that genomic regions of segmental duplication and amplification induce an extended genotype space where a subset of genotypes will exhibit heavily skewed allelic distributions in SNVs (and therefore render them undetectable by methods that assume diploidy). We introduce the concept of modelling allelic counts from sequencing data using a panel of Binomial mixture models where the number of mixtures for a given locus in the genome is informed by a discrete copy number state given as input. We applied CoNAn-SNV to a previously published whole genome shotgun data set obtained from a lobular breast cancer and show that it is able to discover 21 experimentally revalidated somatic non-synonymous mutations in a lobular breast cancer genome that were not detected using copy number insensitive SNV detection algorithms. Importantly, ROC analysis shows that the increased sensitivity of CoNAn-SNV does not result in disproportionate loss of specificity. This was also supported by analysis of a recently published lymphoma genome with a relatively quiescent karyotype, where CoNAn-SNV showed similar results to other callers except in regions of copy number gain where increased sensitivity was conferred. Our results indicate that in genomically unstable tumors, copy number annotation for SNV detection will be critical to fully characterize the mutational landscape of cancer genomes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ryan Giuliany</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Ryan-Giuliany"/>
   <updated>2012-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Ryan-Giuliany</id>
   <content type="html">
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>nFuse: discovery of complex genomic rearrangements in cancer using high-throughput sequencing.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22745232"/>
   <updated>2012-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22745232</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22745232&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complex genomic rearrangements (CGRs) are emerging as a new feature of cancer genomes. CGRs are characterized by multiple genomic breakpoints and thus have the potential to simultaneously affect multiple genes, fusing some genes and interrupting other genes. Analysis of high-throughput whole-genome shotgun sequencing (WGSS) is beginning to facilitate the discovery and characterization of CGRs, but further development of computational methods is required. We have developed an algorithmic method for identifying CGRs in WGSS data based on shortest alternating paths in breakpoint graphs. Aiming for a method with the highest possible sensitivity, we use breakpoint graphs built from all WGSS data, including sequences with ambiguous genomic origin. Since the majority of cell function is encoded by the transcriptome, we target our search to find CGRs that underlie fusion transcripts predicted from matched high-throughput cDNA sequencing (RNA-seq). We have applied our method, nFuse, to the discovery of CGRs in publicly available data from the well-studied breast cancer cell line HCC1954 and primary prostate tumor sample 963. We first establish the sensitivity and specificity of the nFuse breakpoint prediction and scoring method using breakpoints previously discovered in HCC1954. We then validate five out of six CGRs in HCC1954 and two out of two CGRs in 963. We show examples of gene fusions that would be difficult to discover using methods that do not account for the existence of CGRs, including one important event that was missed in a previous study of the HCC1954 genome. Finally, we illustrate how CGRs may be used to infer the gene expression history of a tumor.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Use of mutation profiles to refine the classification of endometrial carcinomas.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22653804"/>
   <updated>2012-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22653804</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22653804&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classification of endometrial carcinomas is based on pathological assessment of tumour cell type; the different cell types (endometrioid, serous, carcinosarcoma, mixed, undifferentiated, and clear cell) are associated with distinct molecular alterations. This current classification system for high-grade subtypes, in particular the distinction between high-grade endometrioid (EEC-3) and serous carcinomas (ESC), is limited in its reproducibility and prognostic abilities. Therefore, a search for specific molecular classifiers to improve endometrial carcinoma subclassification is warranted. We performed target enrichment sequencing on 393 endometrial carcinomas from two large cohorts, sequencing exons from the following nine genes: ARID1A, PPP2R1A, PTEN, PIK3CA, KRAS, CTNNB1, TP53, BRAF, and PPP2R5C. Based on this gene panel, each endometrial carcinoma subtype shows a distinct mutation profile. EEC-3s have significantly different frequencies of PTEN and TP53 mutations when compared to low-grade endometrioid carcinomas. ESCs and EEC-3s are distinct subtypes with significantly different frequencies of mutations in PTEN, ARID1A, PPP2R1A, TP53, and CTNNB1. From the mutation profiles, we were able to identify subtype outliers, ie cases diagnosed morphologically as one subtype but with a mutation profile suggestive of a different subtype. Careful review of these diagnostically challenging cases suggested that the original morphological classification was incorrect in most instances. The molecular profile of carcinosarcomas suggests two distinct mutation profiles for these tumours: endometrioid-type (PTEN, PIK3CA, ARID1A, KRAS mutations) and serous-type (TP53 and PPP2R1A mutations). While this nine-gene panel does not allow for a purely molecularly based classification of endometrial carcinoma, it may prove useful as an adjunct to morphological classification and serve as an aid in the classification of problematic cases. If used in practice, it may lead to improved diagnostic reproducibility and may also serve to stratify patients for targeted therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Integrative analysis of genome-wide loss of heterozygosity and monoallelic expression at nucleotide resolution reveals disrupted pathways in triple-negative breast cancer.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22637570"/>
   <updated>2012-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22637570</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22637570&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loss of heterozygosity (LOH) and copy number alteration (CNA) feature prominently in the somatic genomic landscape of tumors. As such, karyotypic aberrations in cancer genomes have been studied extensively to discover novel oncogenes and tumor-suppressor genes. Advances in sequencing technology have enabled the cost-effective detection of tumor genome and transcriptome mutation events at single-base-pair resolution; however, computational methods for predicting segmental regions of LOH in this context are not yet fully explored. Consequently, whole transcriptome, nucleotide-level resolution analysis of monoallelic expression patterns associated with LOH has not yet been undertaken in cancer. We developed a novel approach for inference of LOH from paired tumor/normal sequence data and applied it to a cohort of 23 triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) genomes. Following extensive benchmarking experiments, we describe the nucleotide-resolution landscape of LOH in TNBC and assess the consequent effect of LOH on the transcriptomes of these tumors using RNA-seq-derived measurements of allele-specific expression. We show that the majority of monoallelic expression in the transcriptomes of triple-negative breast cancer can be explained by genomic regions of LOH and establish an upper bound for monoallelic expression that may be explained by other tumor-specific modifications such as epigenetics or mutations. Monoallelically expressed genes associated with LOH reveal that cell cycle, homologous recombination and actin-cytoskeletal functions are putatively disrupted by LOH in TNBC. Finally, we show how inference of LOH can be used to interpret allele frequencies of somatic mutations and postulate on temporal ordering of mutations in the evolutionary history of these tumors.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The genomic and transcriptomic architecture of 2,000 breast tumours reveals novel subgroups.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22522925"/>
   <updated>2012-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22522925</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22522925&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The elucidation of breast cancer subgroups and their molecular drivers requires integrated views of the genome and transcriptome from representative numbers of patients. We present an integrated analysis of copy number and gene expression in a discovery and validation set of 997 and 995 primary breast tumours, respectively, with long-term clinical follow-up. Inherited variants (copy number variants and single nucleotide polymorphisms) and acquired somatic copy number aberrations (CNAs) were associated with expression in ~40% of genes, with the landscape dominated by cis- and trans-acting CNAs. By delineating expression outlier genes driven in cis by CNAs, we identified putative cancer genes, including deletions in PPP2R2A, MTAP and MAP2K4. Unsupervised analysis of paired DNA–RNA profiles revealed novel subgroups with distinct clinical outcomes, which reproduced in the validation cohort. These include a high-risk, oestrogen-receptor-positive 11q13/14 cis-acting subgroup and a favourable prognosis subgroup devoid of CNAs. Trans-acting aberration hotspots were found to modulate subgroup-specific gene networks, including a TCR deletion-mediated adaptive immune response in the ‘CNA-devoid’ subgroup and a basal-specific chromosome 5 deletion-associated mitotic network. Our results provide a novel molecular stratification of the breast cancer population, derived from the impact of somatic CNAs on the transcriptome.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The clonal and mutational evolution spectrum of primary triple-negative breast cancers.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22495314"/>
   <updated>2012-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22495314</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22495314&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primary triple-negative breast cancers (TNBCs), a tumour type defined by lack of oestrogen receptor, progesterone receptor and ERBB2 gene amplification, represent approximately 16% of all breast cancers. Here we show in 104 TNBC cases that at the time of diagnosis these cancers exhibit a wide and continuous spectrum of genomic evolution, with some having only a handful of coding somatic aberrations in a few pathways, whereas others contain hundreds of coding somatic mutations. High-throughput RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) revealed that only approximately 36% of mutations are expressed. Using deep re-sequencing measurements of allelic abundance for 2,414 somatic mutations, we determine for the first time-to our knowledge-in an epithelial tumour subtype, the relative abundance of clonal frequencies among cases representative of the population. We show that TNBCs vary widely in their clonal frequencies at the time of diagnosis, with the basal subtype of TNBC showing more variation than non-basal TNBC. Although p53 (also known as TP53), PIK3CA and PTEN somatic mutations seem to be clonally dominant compared to other genes, in some tumours their clonal frequencies are incompatible with founder status. Mutations in cytoskeletal, cell shape and motility proteins occurred at lower clonal frequencies, suggesting that they occurred later during tumour progression. Taken together, our results show that understanding the biology and therapeutic responses of patients with TNBC will require the determination of individual tumour clonal genotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>JointSNVMix: a probabilistic model for accurate detection of somatic mutations in normal/tumour paired next-generation sequencing data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22285562"/>
   <updated>2012-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22285562</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22285562&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identification of somatic single nucleotide variants (SNVs) in tumour genomes is a necessary step in defining the mutational landscapes of cancers. Experimental designs for genome-wide ascertainment of somatic mutations now routinely include next-generation sequencing (NGS) of tumour DNA and matched constitutional DNA from the same individual. This allows investigators to control for germline polymorphisms and distinguish somatic mutations that are unique to the tumour, thus reducing the burden of labour-intensive and expensive downstream experiments needed to verify initial predictions. In order to make full use of such paired datasets, computational tools for simultaneous analysis of tumour-normal paired sequence data are required, but are currently under-developed and under-represented in the bioinformatics literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this contribution, we introduce two novel probabilistic graphical models called JointSNVMix1 and JointSNVMix2 for jointly analysing paired tumour-normal digital allelic count data from NGS experiments. In contrast to independent analysis of the tumour and normal data, our method allows statistical strength to be borrowed across the samples and therefore amplifies the statistical power to identify and distinguish both germline and somatic events in a unified probabilistic framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The JointSNVMix models and four other models discussed in the article are part of the JointSNVMix software package available for download at http://compbio.bccrc.ca&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sshah@bccrc.ca&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations correlate with TP53 abnormalities and presence of immune cell infiltrates in ovarian high-grade serous carcinoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22282309"/>
   <updated>2012-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22282309</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22282309&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We characterized BRCA1 and BRCA2 status (mutation/methylation) in a consecutive series of cases of ovarian carcinoma in order to identify differences in clinicopathological features, molecular characteristics, and outcome between the pelvic high-grade serous cancers with (i) germline or somatic mutations in BRCA1 or BRCA2, (ii) methylation of BRCA1, and (iii) normal BRCA1 or BRCA2. In all, 131 women were identified prospectively, who were undergoing surgical staging and agreed to germline testing for BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations. Histopathology, germline and somatic BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutations, BRCA1 methylation, and BRCA1 and BRCA2 mRNA expression levels distinguished four subgroups. In all, 103 cases were high-grade serous carcinoma and of these 31 (30%) had germline or somatic BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutations (20% BRCA1 and 10% BRCA2) (group 1), 21 (20%) had methylation of BRCA1 (group 2), and in 51 (50%) there was no BRCA loss (group 3). Group 4 consisted of 28 cases of non-high-grade serous, none of which had BRCA loss. BRCA1 and BRCA2 mRNA expression levels correlated with designated group (P=0.0008). Among high-grade serous carcinomas, there were no differences between groups 1-3 with respect to stage, ascites, CA125 level, platinum sensitivity, cytoreduction rate, neoadjuvant chemotherapy, or survival. Tumors with BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutations had increased immune infiltrates (CD20 and TIA-1) compared with high-grade serous without mutations (P=0.034, 0.027). TP53 expression differed between groups (P&amp;lt;0.0001), with abnormal TP53 expression in 49/50 tumors from groups 1 and 2. Wild-type TP53 expression was associated with worse outcome in high-grade serous (P&amp;lt;0.001). BRCA loss (mutation/methylation) is a common event in the pelvic high-grade serous (50%). TP53 abnormalities and increased immune cell infiltrates are significantly more common in high-grade serous with germline and somatic mutations in BRCA1 or BRCA2, compared with tumors lacking BRCA abnormalities.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>14-3-3 fusion oncogenes in high-grade endometrial stromal sarcoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22223660"/>
   <updated>2012-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22223660</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22223660&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14-3-3 proteins are ubiquitously expressed regulators of various cellular functions, including proliferation, metabolism, and differentiation, and altered 14-3-3 expression is associated with development and progression of cancer. We report a transforming 14-3-3 oncoprotein, which we identified through conventional cytogenetics and whole-transcriptome sequencing analysis as a highly recurrent genetic mechanism in a clinically aggressive form of uterine sarcoma: high-grade endometrial stromal sarcoma (ESS). The 14-3-3 oncoprotein results from a t(10;17) genomic rearrangement, leading to fusion between 14-3-3ε (YWHAE) and either of two nearly identical FAM22 family members (FAM22A or FAM22B). Expression of YWHAE-FAM22 fusion oncoproteins was demonstrated by immunoblot in t(10;17)-bearing frozen tumor and cell line samples. YWHAE-FAM22 fusion gene knockdowns were performed with shRNAs and siRNAs targeting various FAM22A exons in an t(10;17)-bearing ESS cell line (ESS1): Fusion protein expression was inhibited, with corresponding reduction in cell growth and migration. YWHAE-FAM22 maintains a structurally and functionally intact 14-3-3ε (YWHAE) protein-binding domain, which is directed to the nucleus by a FAM22 nuclear localization sequence. In contrast to classic ESS, harboring JAZF1 genetic fusions, YWHAE-FAM22 ESS display high-grade histologic features, a distinct gene-expression profile, and a more aggressive clinical course. Fluorescence in situ hybridization analysis demonstrated absolute specificity of YWHAE-FAM22A/B genetic rearrangement for high-grade ESS, with no fusions detected in other uterine and nonuterine mesenchymal tumors (55 tumor types, n = 827). These discoveries reveal diagnostically and therapeutically relevant models for characterizing aberrant 14-3-3 oncogenic functions.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Recurrent somatic DICER1 mutations in nonepithelial ovarian cancers.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22187960"/>
   <updated>2011-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22187960</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22187960&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Germline truncating mutations in DICER1, an endoribonuclease in the RNase III family that is essential for processing microRNAs, have been observed in families with the pleuropulmonary blastoma-family tumor and dysplasia syndrome. Mutation carriers are at risk for nonepithelial ovarian tumors, notably sex cord-stromal tumors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sequenced the whole transcriptomes or exomes of 14 nonepithelial ovarian tumors and noted closely clustered mutations in the region of DICER1 encoding the RNase IIIb domain of DICER1 in four samples. We then sequenced this region of DICER1 in additional ovarian tumors and in certain other tumors and queried the effect of the mutations on the enzymatic activity of DICER1 using in vitro RNA cleavage assays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DICER1 mutations in the RNase IIIb domain were found in 30 of 102 nonepithelial ovarian tumors (29%), predominantly in Sertoli-Leydig cell tumors (26 of 43, or 60%), including 4 tumors with additional germline DICER1 mutations. These mutations were restricted to codons encoding metal-binding sites within the RNase IIIb catalytic centers, which are critical for microRNA interaction and cleavage, and were somatic in all 16 samples in which germline DNA was available for testing. We also detected mutations in 1 of 14 nonseminomatous testicular germ-cell tumors, in 2 of 5 embryonal rhabdomyosarcomas, and in 1 of 266 epithelial ovarian and endometrial carcinomas. The mutant DICER1 proteins had reduced RNase IIIb activity but retained RNase IIIa activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somatic missense mutations affecting the RNase IIIb domain of DICER1 are common in nonepithelial ovarian tumors. These mutations do not obliterate DICER1 function but alter it in specific cell types, a novel mechanism through which perturbation of microRNA processing may be oncogenic. (Funded by the Terry Fox Research Institute and others.).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Feature-based classifiers for somatic mutation detection in tumour-normal paired sequencing data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/22084253"/>
   <updated>2011-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/22084253</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22084253&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of cancer genomes now routinely involves using next-generation sequencing technology (NGS) to profile tumours for single nucleotide variant (SNV) somatic mutations. However, surprisingly few published bioinformatics methods exist for the specific purpose of identifying somatic mutations from NGS data and existing tools are often inaccurate, yielding intolerably high false prediction rates. As such, the computational problem of accurately inferring somatic mutations from paired tumour/normal NGS data remains an unsolved challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We present the comparison of four standard supervised machine learning algorithms for the purpose of somatic SNV prediction in tumour/normal NGS experiments. To evaluate these approaches (random forest, Bayesian additive regression tree, support vector machine and logistic regression), we constructed 106 features representing 3369 candidate somatic SNVs from 48 breast cancer genomes, originally predicted with naive methods and subsequently revalidated to establish ground truth labels. We trained the classifiers on this data (consisting of 1015 true somatic mutations and 2354 non-somatic mutation positions) and conducted a rigorous evaluation of these methods using a cross-validation framework and hold-out test NGS data from both exome capture and whole genome shotgun platforms. All learning algorithms employing predictive discriminative approaches with feature selection improved the predictive accuracy over standard approaches by statistically significant margins. In addition, using unsupervised clustering of the ground truth ‘false positive’ predictions, we noted several distinct classes and present evidence suggesting non-overlapping sources of technical artefacts illuminating important directions for future study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software called MutationSeq and datasets are available from http://compbio.bccrc.ca.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using next-generation sequencing for the diagnosis of rare disorders: a family with retinitis pigmentosa and skeletal abnormalities.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/21792934"/>
   <updated>2011-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/21792934</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;21792934&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linkage analysis with subsequent candidate gene sequencing is typically used to diagnose novel inherited syndromes. It is now possible to expedite diagnosis through the sequencing of all coding regions of the genome (the exome) or full genomes. We sequenced the exomes of four members of a family presenting with spondylo-epiphyseal dysplasia and retinitis pigmentosa and identified a six-base-pair (6-bp) deletion in GNPTG, the gene implicated in mucolipidosis type IIIγ. The diagnosis was confirmed by biochemical studies and both broadens the mucolipidosis type III phenotype and demonstrates the clinical utility of next-generation sequencing to diagnose rare genetic diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>deFuse: an algorithm for gene fusion discovery in tumor RNA-Seq data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/21625565"/>
   <updated>2011-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/21625565</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;21625565&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gene fusions created by somatic genomic rearrangements are known to play an important role in the onset and development of some cancers, such as lymphomas and sarcomas. RNA-Seq (whole transcriptome shotgun sequencing) is proving to be a useful tool for the discovery of novel gene fusions in cancer transcriptomes. However, algorithmic methods for the discovery of gene fusions using RNA-Seq data remain underdeveloped. We have developed deFuse, a novel computational method for fusion discovery in tumor RNA-Seq data. Unlike existing methods that use only unique best-hit alignments and consider only fusion boundaries at the ends of known exons, deFuse considers all alignments and all possible locations for fusion boundaries. As a result, deFuse is able to identify fusion sequences with demonstrably better sensitivity than previous approaches. To increase the specificity of our approach, we curated a list of 60 true positive and 61 true negative fusion sequences (as confirmed by RT-PCR), and have trained an adaboost classifier on 11 novel features of the sequence data. The resulting classifier has an estimated value of 0.91 for the area under the ROC curve. We have used deFuse to discover gene fusions in 40 ovarian tumor samples, one ovarian cancer cell line, and three sarcoma samples. We report herein the first gene fusions discovered in ovarian cancer. We conclude that gene fusions are not infrequent events in ovarian cancer and that these events have the potential to substantially alter the expression patterns of the genes involved; gene fusions should therefore be considered in efforts to comprehensively characterize the mutational profiles of ovarian cancer transcriptomes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Comrad: detection of expressed rearrangements by integrated analysis of RNA-Seq and low coverage genome sequence data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/21478487"/>
   <updated>2011-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/21478487</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;21478487&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comrad is a novel algorithmic framework for the integrated analysis of RNA-Seq and whole genome shotgun sequencing (WGSS) data for the purposes of discovering genomic rearrangements and aberrant transcripts. The Comrad framework leverages the advantages of both RNA-Seq and WGSS data, providing accurate classification of rearrangements as expressed or not expressed and accurate classification of the genomic or non-genomic origin of aberrant transcripts. A major benefit of Comrad is its ability to accurately identify aberrant transcripts and associated rearrangements using low coverage genome data. As a result, a Comrad analysis can be performed at a cost comparable to that of two RNA-Seq experiments, significantly lower than an analysis requiring high coverage genome data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have applied Comrad to the discovery of gene fusions and read-throughs in prostate cancer cell line C4-2, a derivative of the LNCaP cell line with androgen-independent characteristics. As a proof of concept, we have rediscovered in the C4-2 data 4 of the 6 fusions previously identified in LNCaP. We also identified six novel fusion transcripts and associated genomic breakpoints, and verified their existence in LNCaP, suggesting that Comrad may be more sensitive than previous methods that have been applied to fusion discovery in LNCaP. We show that many of the gene fusions discovered using Comrad would be difficult to identify using currently available techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A C++ and Perl implementation of the method demonstrated in this article is available at http://compbio.cs.sfu.ca/.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Subtype-specific mutation of PPP2R1A in endometrial and ovarian carcinomas.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/21381030"/>
   <updated>2011-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/21381030</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;21381030&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PPP2R1A mutations have recently been described in 3/42 (7%) of clear cell carcinomas of the ovary. PPP2R1A encodes the α-isoform of the scaffolding subunit of the serine/threonine protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A) holoenzyme. This putative tumour suppressor complex is involved in growth and survival pathways. Through targeted sequencing of PPP2R1A, we identified somatic missense mutations in 40.8% (20/49) of high-grade serous endometrial tumours, and 5.0% (3/60) of endometrial endometrioid carcinomas. Mutations were also identified in ovarian tumours at lower frequencies: 12.2% (5/41) of endometrioid and 4.1% (2/49) of clear cell carcinomas. No mutations were found in 50 high-grade and 12 low-grade serous carcinomas. Amino acid residues affected by these mutations are highly conserved across species and are involved in direct interactions with regulatory B-subunits of the PP2A holoenzyme. PPP2R1A mutations in endometrial high-grade serous carcinomas are a frequent and potentially targetable feature of this disease. The finding of frequent PPP2R1A mutations in high-grade serous carcinoma of the endometrium but not in high-grade serous carcinoma of the ovary provides clear genetic evidence that these are distinct diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MHC class II transactivator CIITA is a recurrent gene fusion partner in lymphoid cancers.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/21368758"/>
   <updated>2011-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/21368758</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;21368758&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chromosomal translocations are critically involved in the molecular pathogenesis of B-cell lymphomas, and highly recurrent and specific rearrangements have defined distinct molecular subtypes linked to unique clinicopathological features. In contrast, several well-characterized lymphoma entities still lack disease-defining translocation events. To identify novel fusion transcripts resulting from translocations, we investigated two Hodgkin lymphoma cell lines by whole-transcriptome paired-end sequencing (RNA-seq). Here we show a highly expressed gene fusion involving the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class II transactivator CIITA (MHC2TA) in KM-H2 cells. In a subsequent evaluation of 263 B-cell lymphomas, we also demonstrate that genomic CIITA breaks are highly recurrent in primary mediastinal B-cell lymphoma (38%) and classical Hodgkin lymphoma (cHL) (15%). Furthermore, we find that CIITA is a promiscuous partner of various in-frame gene fusions, and we report that CIITA gene alterations impact survival in primary mediastinal B-cell lymphoma (PMBCL). As functional consequences of CIITA gene fusions, we identify downregulation of surface HLA class II expression and overexpression of ligands of the receptor molecule programmed cell death 1 (CD274/PDL1 and CD273/PDL2). These receptor-ligand interactions have been shown to impact anti-tumour immune responses in several cancers, whereas decreased MHC class II expression has been linked to reduced tumour cell immunogenicity. Thus, our findings suggest that recurrent rearrangements of CIITA may represent a novel genetic mechanism underlying tumour-microenvironment interactions across a spectrum of lymphoid cancers.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ARID1A mutations in endometriosis-associated ovarian carcinomas.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/20942669"/>
   <updated>2010-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/20942669</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20942669&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovarian clear-cell and endometrioid carcinomas may arise from endometriosis, but the molecular events involved in this transformation have not been described.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sequenced the whole transcriptomes of 18 ovarian clear-cell carcinomas and 1 ovarian clear-cell carcinoma cell line and found somatic mutations in ARID1A (the AT-rich interactive domain 1A [SWI-like] gene) in 6 of the samples. ARID1A encodes BAF250a, a key component of the SWI–SNF chromatin remodeling complex. We sequenced ARID1A in an additional 210 ovarian carcinomas and a second ovarian clear-cell carcinoma cell line and measured BAF250a expression by means of immunohistochemical analysis in an additional 455 ovarian carcinomas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ARID1A mutations were seen in 55 of 119 ovarian clear-cell carcinomas (46%), 10 of 33 endometrioid carcinomas (30%), and none of the 76 high-grade serous ovarian carcinomas. Seventeen carcinomas had two somatic mutations each. Loss of the BAF250a protein correlated strongly with the ovarian clear-cell carcinoma and endometrioid carcinoma subtypes and the presence of ARID1A mutations. In two patients, ARID1A mutations and loss of BAF250a expression were evident in the tumor and contiguous atypical endometriosis but not in distant endometriotic lesions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These data implicate ARID1A as a tumor-suppressor gene frequently disrupted in ovarian clear-cell and endometrioid carcinomas. Since ARID1A mutation and loss of BAF250a can be seen in the preneoplastic lesions, we speculate that this is an early event in the transformation of endometriosis into cancer. (Funded by the British Columbia Cancer Foundation and the Vancouver General Hospital–University of British Columbia Hospital Foundation.).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Acquired TNFRSF14 mutations in follicular lymphoma are associated with worse prognosis.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/20884631"/>
   <updated>2010-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/20884631</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20884631&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical correlative studies have linked 1p36 deletions with worse prognosis in follicular lymphoma (FL). In this study, we sought to identify the critical gene(s) in this region that is responsible for conferring inferior prognosis. BAC array technology applied to 141 FL specimens detected a minimum region of deletion (MRD) of ∼97 kb within 1p36.32 in 20% of these cases. Frequent single-nucleotide polymorphism-detected copy-neutral loss of heterozygosity was also found in this region. Analysis of promoter CpGs in the MRD did not reveal differential patterns of DNA methylation in samples that differed in 1p36 status. Exon sequencing of MRD genes identified somatic alterations in the TNFRSF14 gene in 3 of 11 selected cases with matching normal DNA. An expanded cohort consisting of 251 specimens identified 46 cases (18.3%) with nonsynonymous mutations affecting TNFRSF14. Overall survival (OS) and disease-specific survival (DSS) were associated with the presence of TNFRSF14 mutation in patients whose overall treatment included rituximab. We further showed that inferior OS and DSS were most pronounced in patients whose lymphomas contained both TNFRSF14 mutations and 1p36 deletions after adjustment for the International Prognostic Index [hazard ratios of 3.65 (95% confidence interval, 1.35-9.878, P=0.011) and 3.19 (95% confidence interval, 1.06-9.57, P=0.039), respectively]. Our findings identify TNFRSF14 as a candidate gene associated with a subset of FL, based on frequent occurrence of acquired mutations and their correlation with inferior clinical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Evolution of an adenocarcinoma in response to selection by targeted kinase inhibitors.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/20696054"/>
   <updated>2010-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/20696054</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20696054&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adenocarcinomas of the tongue are rare and represent the minority (20 to 25%) of salivary gland tumors affecting the tongue. We investigated the utility of massively parallel sequencing to characterize an adenocarcinoma of the tongue, before and after treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the pre-treatment tumor we identified 7,629 genes within regions of copy number gain. There were 1,078 genes that exhibited increased expression relative to the blood and unrelated tumors and four genes contained somatic protein-coding mutations. Our analysis suggested the tumor cells were driven by the RET oncogene. Genes whose protein products are targeted by the RET inhibitors sunitinib and sorafenib correlated with being amplified and or highly expressed. Consistent with our observations, administration of sunitinib was associated with stable disease lasting 4 months, after which the lung lesions began to grow. Administration of sorafenib and sulindac provided disease stabilization for an additional 3 months after which the cancer progressed and new lesions appeared. A recurring metastasis possessed 7,288 genes within copy number amplicons, 385 genes exhibiting increased expression relative to other tumors and 9 new somatic protein coding mutations. The observed mutations and amplifications were consistent with therapeutic resistance arising through activation of the MAPK and AKT pathways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conclude that complete genomic characterization of a rare tumor has the potential to aid in clinical decision making and identifying therapeutic approaches where no established treatment protocols exist. These results also provide direct in vivo genomic evidence for mutational evolution within a tumor under drug selection and potential mechanisms of drug resistance accrual.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>High resolution analysis of follicular lymphoma genomes reveals somatic recurrent sites of copy-neutral loss of heterozygosity and copy number alterations that target single genes.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/20544841"/>
   <updated>2010-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/20544841</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20544841&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A multiplatform approach, including conventional cytogenetic techniques, BAC array comparative genomic hybridization, and Affymetrix 500K SNP arrays, was applied to the study of the tumor genomes of 25 follicular lymphoma biopsy samples with paired normal DNA samples to characterize balanced translocations, copy number imbalances, and copy-neutral loss of heterozygosity (cnLOH). In addition to the t(14;18), eight unique balanced translocations were found. Commonly reported FL-associated copy number regions were revealed including losses of 1p32-36, 6q, and 10q, and gains of 1q, 6p, 7, 12, 18, and X. The most frequent regions affected by copy-neutral loss of heterozygosity were 1p36.33 (28%), 6p21.3 (20%), 12q21.2-q24.33 (16%), and 16p13.3 (24%). We also identified by SNP analysis, 45 aberrant regions that each affected one gene, including CDKN2A, CDKN2B, FHIT, KIT, PEX14, and PTPRD, which were associated with canonical pathways involved in tumor development. This study illustrates the power of using complementary high-resolution platforms on paired tumor/normal specimens and computational analysis to provide potential insights into the significance of single-gene somatic aberrations in FL tumorigenesis.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Genome-wide copy number analysis of Hodgkin Reed-Sternberg cells identifies recurrent imbalances with correlations to treatment outcome.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/20339089"/>
   <updated>2010-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/20339089</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20339089&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In classical Hodgkin lymphoma (cHL) the mechanisms underlying primary refractory disease and relapse remain unknown. To gain further insight into cHL pathogenesis and genomic changes linked to treatment response, we studied 53 cHL patients by array comparative genomic hybridization, including 23 patients whose primary treatment failed, using DNA from microdissected HRS cells. Copy number alterations found in more than 20% of cases included gains of 2p, 9p, 16p, 17q, 19q, 20q, and losses of 6q, 11q, and 13q. We identified at high resolution recurrent changes defining minimally gained and lost regions harboring genes involved in nuclear factor kappaB signaling, such as REL, IKBKB, CD40, and MAP3K14. Gains of chromosome 16p11.2-13.3 were significantly more frequent in pretreatment and relapse biopsies of unresponsive patients and were associated with shortened disease-specific survival (P = .028). In the therapy-resistant HL cell line KMH2, we found genomic gains and overexpression of the multidrug resistance gene ABCC1 mapping to cytoband 16p13.11. We show that doxorubicin exposure to KMH2 induces ABCC1 expression and that siRNA silencing of ABCC1 sensitizes KMH2 cells to doxorubicin toxicity in vitro, suggesting that overexpression of ABCC1 contributes to the drug resistance phenotype found in KMH2.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Tumor-associated macrophages and survival in classic Hodgkin's lymphoma.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/20220182"/>
   <updated>2010-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/20220182</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20220182&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite advances in treatments for Hodgkin’s lymphoma, about 20% of patients still die from progressive disease. Current prognostic models predict the outcome of treatment with imperfect accuracy, and clinically relevant biomarkers have not been established to improve on the International Prognostic Score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using gene-expression profiling, we analyzed 130 frozen samples obtained from patients with classic Hodgkin’s lymphoma during diagnostic lymph-node biopsy to determine which cellular signatures were correlated with treatment outcome. We confirmed our findings in an independent cohort of 166 patients, using immunohistochemical analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gene-expression profiling identified a gene signature of tumor-associated macrophages that was significantly associated with primary treatment failure (P=0.02). In an independent cohort of patients, we found that an increased number of CD68+ macrophages was correlated with a shortened progression-free survival (P=0.03) and with an increased likelihood of relapse after autologous hematopoietic stem-cell transplantation (P=0.008), resulting in shortened disease-specific survival (P=0.003). In multivariate analysis, this adverse prognostic factor outperformed the International Prognostic Score for disease-specific survival (P=0.003 vs. P=0.03). The absence of an elevated number of CD68+ cells in patients with limited-stage disease defined a subgroup of patients with a long-term disease-specific survival of 100% with the use of current treatment strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An increased number of tumor-associated macrophages was strongly associated with shortened survival in patients with classic Hodgkin’s lymphoma and provides a new biomarker for risk stratification.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>SNVMix: predicting single nucleotide variants from next-generation sequencing of tumors.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/20130035"/>
   <updated>2010-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/20130035</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20130035&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next-generation sequencing (NGS) has enabled whole genome and transcriptome single nucleotide variant (SNV) discovery in cancer. NGS produces millions of short sequence reads that, once aligned to a reference genome sequence, can be interpreted for the presence of SNVs. Although tools exist for SNV discovery from NGS data, none are specifically suited to work with data from tumors, where altered ploidy and tumor cellularity impact the statistical expectations of SNV discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We developed three implementations of a probabilistic Binomial mixture model, called SNVMix, designed to infer SNVs from NGS data from tumors to address this problem. The first models allelic counts as observations and infers SNVs and model parameters using an expectation maximization (EM) algorithm and is therefore capable of adjusting to deviation of allelic frequencies inherent in genomically unstable tumor genomes. The second models nucleotide and mapping qualities of the reads by probabilistically weighting the contribution of a read/nucleotide to the inference of a SNV based on the confidence we have in the base call and the read alignment. The third combines filtering out low-quality data in addition to probabilistic weighting of the qualities. We quantitatively evaluated these approaches on 16 ovarian cancer RNASeq datasets with matched genotyping arrays and a human breast cancer genome sequenced to &amp;gt;40x (haploid) coverage with ground truth data and show systematically that the SNVMix models outperform competing approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software and data are available at http://compbio.bccrc.ca&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sshah@bccrc.ca SUPPLEMANTARY INFORMATION: Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Somatic mutations altering EZH2 (Tyr641) in follicular and diffuse large B-cell lymphomas of germinal-center origin.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/20081860"/>
   <updated>2010-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/20081860</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20081860&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follicular lymphoma (FL) and the GCB subtype of diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) derive from germinal center B cells. Targeted resequencing studies have revealed mutations in various genes encoding proteins in the NF-kappaB pathway that contribute to the activated B-cell (ABC) DLBCL subtype, but thus far few GCB-specific mutations have been identified. Here we report recurrent somatic mutations affecting the polycomb-group oncogene EZH2, which encodes a histone methyltransferase responsible for trimethylating Lys27 of histone H3 (H3K27). After the recent discovery of mutations in KDM6A (UTX), which encodes the histone H3K27me3 demethylase UTX, in several cancer types, EZH2 is the second histone methyltransferase gene found to be mutated in cancer. These mutations, which result in the replacement of a single tyrosine in the SET domain of the EZH2 protein (Tyr641), occur in 21.7% of GCB DLBCLs and 7.2% of FLs and are absent from ABC DLBCLs. Our data are consistent with the notion that EZH2 proteins with mutant Tyr641 have reduced enzymatic activity in vitro.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mutational evolution in a lobular breast tumour profiled at single nucleotide resolution.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/19812674"/>
   <updated>2009-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/19812674</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;19812674&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in next generation sequencing have made it possible to precisely characterize all somatic coding mutations that occur during the development and progression of individual cancers. Here we used these approaches to sequence the genomes (&amp;gt;43-fold coverage) and transcriptomes of an oestrogen-receptor-alpha-positive metastatic lobular breast cancer at depth. We found 32 somatic non-synonymous coding mutations present in the metastasis, and measured the frequency of these somatic mutations in DNA from the primary tumour of the same patient, which arose 9 years earlier. Five of the 32 mutations (in ABCB11, HAUS3, SLC24A4, SNX4 and PALB2) were prevalent in the DNA of the primary tumour removed at diagnosis 9 years earlier, six (in KIF1C, USP28, MYH8, MORC1, KIAA1468 and RNASEH2A) were present at lower frequencies (1-13%), 19 were not detected in the primary tumour, and two were undetermined. The combined analysis of genome and transcriptome data revealed two new RNA-editing events that recode the amino acid sequence of SRP9 and COG3. Taken together, our data show that single nucleotide mutational heterogeneity can be a property of low or intermediate grade primary breast cancers and that significant evolution can occur with disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mutation of FOXL2 in granulosa-cell tumors of the ovary.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/19516027"/>
   <updated>2009-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/19516027</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;19516027&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granulosa-cell tumors (GCTs) are the most common type of malignant ovarian sex cord-stromal tumor (SCST). The pathogenesis of these tumors is unknown. Moreover, their histopathological diagnosis can be challenging, and there is no curative treatment beyond surgery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We analyzed four adult-type GCTs using whole-transcriptome paired-end RNA sequencing. We identified putative GCT-specific mutations that were present in at least three of these samples but were absent from the transcriptomes of 11 epithelial ovarian tumors, published human genomes, and databases of single-nucleotide polymorphisms. We confirmed these variants by direct sequencing of complementary DNA and genomic DNA. We then analyzed additional tumors and matched normal genomic DNA, using a combination of direct sequencing, analyses of restriction-fragment-length polymorphisms, and TaqMan assays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All four index GCTs had a missense point mutation, 402C–&amp;gt;G (C134W), in FOXL2, a gene encoding a transcription factor known to be critical for granulosa-cell development. The FOXL2 mutation was present in 86 of 89 additional adult-type GCTs (97%), in 3 of 14 thecomas (21%), and in 1 of 10 juvenile-type GCTs (10%). The mutation was absent in 49 SCSTs of other types and in 329 unrelated ovarian or breast tumors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole-transcriptome sequencing of four GCTs identified a single, recurrent somatic mutation (402C–&amp;gt;G) in FOXL2 that was present in almost all morphologically identified adult-type GCTs. Mutant FOXL2 is a potential driver in the pathogenesis of adult-type GCTs.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Model-based clustering of array CGH data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/19478003"/>
   <updated>2009-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/19478003</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;19478003&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis of array comparative genomic hybridization (aCGH) data for recurrent DNA copy number alterations from a cohort of patients can yield distinct sets of molecular signatures or profiles. This can be due to the presence of heterogeneous cancer subtypes within a supposedly homogeneous population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose a novel statistical method for automatically detecting such subtypes or clusters. Our approach is model based: each cluster is defined in terms of a sparse profile, which contains the locations of unusually frequent alterations. The profile is represented as a hidden Markov model. Samples are assigned to clusters based on their similarity to the cluster’s profile. We simultaneously infer the cluster assignments and the cluster profiles using an expectation maximization-like algorithm. We show, using a realistic simulation study, that our method is significantly more accurate than standard clustering techniques. We then apply our method to two clinical datasets. In particular, we examine previously reported aCGH data from a cohort of 106 follicular lymphoma patients, and discover clusters that are known to correspond to clinically relevant subgroups. In addition, we examine a cohort of 92 diffuse large B-cell lymphoma patients, and discover previously unreported clusters of biological interest which have inspired followup clinical research on an independent cohort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software and synthetic datasets are available at http://www.cs.ubc.ca/ approximately sshah/acgh as part of the CNA-HMMer package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supplementary data are available at Bioinformatics online.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Andrew McPherson</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Andrew-McPherson"/>
   <updated>2009-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Andrew-McPherson</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a Postdoctoral Fellow at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pathology.ubc.ca&quot;&gt;Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubc.ca&quot;&gt;University of British Columbia&lt;/a&gt;.  I am interested in understanding how tumour cells evolve in response to the immune system and cancer treatment, with the aim of improving treatment options.  I currently work on the development of computational methods and infrastructure for single cell genome sequencing, with the intention of applying these methods to patient samples and derived xenografts.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Genome-wide profiling of follicular lymphoma by array comparative genomic hybridization reveals prognostically significant DNA copy number imbalances.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/18703704"/>
   <updated>2008-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/18703704</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;18703704&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secondary genetic events associated with follicular lymphoma (FL) progression are not well defined. We applied genome-wide BAC array comparative genomic hybridization to 106 diagnostic biopsies of FL to characterize regional genomic imbalances. Using an analytical approach that defined regions of copy number change as intersections between visual annotations and a Hidden Markov model-based algorithm, we identified 71 regional alterations that were recurrent in at least 10% of cases. These ranged in size from approximately 200 kb to 44 Mb, affecting chromosomes 1, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10, 12, 17, 18, 19, and 22. We also demonstrated by cluster analysis that 46.2% of the 106 cases could be sub-grouped based on the presence of +1q, +6p/6q-, +7, or +18. Survival analysis showed that 21 of the 71 regions correlated significantly with inferior overall survival (OS). Of these 21 regions, 16 were independent predictors of OS using a multivariate Cox model that included the international prognostic index (IPI) score. Two of these 16 regions (1p36.22-p36.33 and 6q21-q24.3) were also predictors of transformation risk and independent of IPI. These prognostic features may be useful to identify high-risk patients as candidates for risk-adapted therapies.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Modeling recurrent DNA copy number alterations in array CGH data.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/17646330"/>
   <updated>2007-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/17646330</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;17646330&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurrent DNA copy number alterations (CNA) measured with array comparative genomic hybridization (aCGH) reveal important molecular features of human genetics and disease. Studying aCGH profiles from a phenotypic group of individuals can determine important recurrent CNA patterns that suggest a strong correlation to the phenotype. Computational approaches to detecting recurrent CNAs from a set of aCGH experiments have typically relied on discretizing the noisy log ratios and subsequently inferring patterns. We demonstrate that this can have the effect of filtering out important signals present in the raw data. In this article we develop statistical models that jointly infer CNA patterns and the discrete labels by borrowing statistical strength across samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose extending single sample aCGH HMMs to the multiple sample case in order to infer shared CNAs. We model recurrent CNAs as a profile encoded by a master sequence of states that generates the samples. We show how to improve on two basic models by performing joint inference of the discrete labels and providing sparsity in the output. We demonstrate on synthetic ground truth data and real data from lung cancer cell lines how these two important features of our model improve results over baseline models. We include standard quantitative metrics and a qualitative assessment on which to base our conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;http://www.cs.ubc.ca/~sshah/acgh.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Integrating copy number polymorphisms into array CGH analysis using a robust HMM.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/16873504"/>
   <updated>2006-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/16873504</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;16873504&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Array comparative genomic hybridization (aCGH) is a pervasive technique used to identify chromosomal aberrations in human diseases, including cancer. Aberrations are defined as regions of increased or decreased DNA copy number, relative to a normal sample. Accurately identifying the locations of these aberrations has many important medical applications. Unfortunately, the observed copy number changes are often corrupted by various sources of noise, making the boundaries hard to detect. One popular current technique uses hidden Markov models (HMMs) to divide the signal into regions of constant copy number called segments; a subsequent classification phase labels each segment as a gain, a loss or neutral. Unfortunately, standard HMMs are sensitive to outliers, causing over-segmentation, where segments erroneously span very short regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose a simple modification that makes the HMM robust to such outliers. More importantly, this modification allows us to exploit prior knowledge about the likely location of “outliers”, which are often due to copy number polymorphisms (CNPs). By “explaining away” these outliers with prior knowledge about the locations of CNPs, we can focus attention on the more clinically relevant aberrated regions. We show significant improvements over the current state of the art technique (DNAcopy with MergeLevels) on previously published data from mantle cell lymphoma cell lines, and on published benchmark synthetic data augmented with outliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source code written in Matlab is available from http://www.cs.ubc.ca/~sshah/acgh.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ulysses - an application for the projection of molecular interactions across species.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/16356269"/>
   <updated>2005-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/16356269</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;16356269&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We developed Ulysses as a user-oriented system that uses a process called Interolog Analysis for the parallel analysis and display of protein interactions detected in various species. Ulysses was designed to perform such Interolog Analysis by the projection of model organism interaction data onto homologous human proteins, and thus serves as an accelerator for the analysis of uncharacterized human proteins. The relevance of projections was assessed and validated against published reference collections. All source code is freely available, and the Ulysses system can be accessed via a web interface http://www.cisreg.ca/ulysses.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Atlas - a data warehouse for integrative bioinformatics.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/15723693"/>
   <updated>2005-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/15723693</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;15723693&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We present a biological data warehouse called Atlas that locally stores and integrates biological sequences, molecular interactions, homology information, functional annotations of genes, and biological ontologies. The goal of the system is to provide data, as well as a software infrastructure for bioinformatics research and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Atlas system is based on relational data models that we developed for each of the source data types. Data stored within these relational models are managed through Structured Query Language (SQL) calls that are implemented in a set of Application Programming Interfaces (APIs). The APIs include three languages: C++, Java, and Perl. The methods in these API libraries are used to construct a set of loader applications, which parse and load the source datasets into the Atlas database, and a set of toolbox applications which facilitate data retrieval. Atlas stores and integrates local instances of GenBank, RefSeq, UniProt, Human Protein Reference Database (HPRD), Biomolecular Interaction Network Database (BIND), Database of Interacting Proteins (DIP), Molecular Interactions Database (MINT), IntAct, NCBI Taxonomy, Gene Ontology (GO), Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man (OMIM), LocusLink, Entrez Gene and HomoloGene. The retrieval APIs and toolbox applications are critical components that offer end-users flexible, easy, integrated access to this data. We present use cases that use Atlas to integrate these sources for genome annotation, inference of molecular interactions across species, and gene-disease associations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Atlas biological data warehouse serves as data infrastructure for bioinformatics research and development. It forms the backbone of the research activities in our laboratory and facilitates the integration of disparate, heterogeneous biological sources of data enabling new scientific inferences. Atlas achieves integration of diverse data sets at two levels. First, Atlas stores data of similar types using common data models, enforcing the relationships between data types. Second, integration is achieved through a combination of APIs, ontology, and tools. The Atlas software is freely available under the GNU General Public License at: http://bioinformatics.ubc.ca/atlas/&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Pegasys: software for executing and integrating analyses of biological sequences.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/15096276"/>
   <updated>2004-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/15096276</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;15096276&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We present Pegasys–a flexible, modular and customizable software system that facilitates the execution and data integration from heterogeneous biological sequence analysis tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pegasys system includes numerous tools for pair-wise and multiple sequence alignment, ab initio gene prediction, RNA gene detection, masking repetitive sequences in genomic DNA as well as filters for database formatting and processing raw output from various analysis tools. We introduce a novel data structure for creating workflows of sequence analyses and a unified data model to store its results. The software allows users to dynamically create analysis workflows at run-time by manipulating a graphical user interface. All non-serial dependent analyses are executed in parallel on a compute cluster for efficiency of data generation. The uniform data model and backend relational database management system of Pegasys allow for results of heterogeneous programs included in the workflow to be integrated and exported into General Feature Format for further analyses in GFF-dependent tools, or GAME XML for import into the Apollo genome editor. The modularity of the design allows for new tools to be added to the system with little programmer overhead. The database application programming interface allows programmatic access to the data stored in the backend through SQL queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pegasys system enables biologists and bioinformaticians to create and manage sequence analysis workflows. The software is released under the Open Source GNU General Public License. All source code and documentation is available for download at http://bioinformatics.ubc.ca/pegasys/.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GeneComber: combining outputs of gene prediction programs for improved results.</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/papers/12835277"/>
   <updated>2003-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/papers/12835277</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;12835277&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recently demonstrated that combining the output from Genscan and HMMgene can provide increased accuracy of gene predictions. We have created a robust software system that runs algorithms previously described on DNA sequences and provides a public web interface to the system for use by the biological community worldwide. The GeneComber system performs ab initio gene prediction by first taking a user inputted DNA sequence and running Genscan and HMMgene. The outputs of Genscan and HMMgene are then integrated using the EUI, GI and EUI_frame algorithms. All results are then stored into a relational database management system (RDBMS) and can then be retrieved through a web interface. The web interface provides a unified view of the GeneComber predictions by graphically overlaying outputs from Genscan, HMMgene, EUI, GI and EUI_frame. Outputs can also be retrieved in general feature format (GFF) or FASTA format. The software is written in the Perl programming language and is both dependent on and interoperable with the Bioperl toolkit. It includes high-level application programming interfaces (APIs) to run Genscan, HMMgene and a database API to insert prediction results into an RDBMS. The APIs are assembled into the genecomber script which is executed by the web interface or can be run directly from the Unix command line. The web interface is written in PHP and is structured so as to be easily modified for viewing data from any database that stores gene structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GeneComber public web interface and supplementary information is located at http://bioinformatics.ubc.ca/genecomber The source code is released under the GNU General Public License and is available at ftp://ftp.bioinformatics.ubc.ca/pub/genecomber/software.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sohrab Shah</title>
   <link href="http://shahlab.ca/team/Sohrab-shah"/>
   <updated>1999-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://shahlab.ca/team/Sohrab-shah</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dr. Shah received a PhD in computer science from UBC in 2008 and was appointed as a Principal Investigator to The BC Cancer Agency and the University of British Columbia in 2010. He holds the Canada Research Chair in Computational Cancer Genomics, and is the recipient of both a Michael Smith Foundation for Health Research Career Investigator Award and a Terry Fox Research Institute New Investigator Award. His research focuses on understanding how tumours evolve over time through integrative approaches involving genomics and computational modeling. He has made seminal contributions to understanding of clonal evolution in ovarian cancer and discovered that specific mutational patterns in the genomes of ovarian cancers are prognostic in terms of treatment outcomes. Dr. Shah has also pioneered computational methods for inference of mutations in cancer genomes as well as deciphering patterns of cancer evolution. He has led development of novel Bayesian statistical models, algorithms, and computational approaches to analyze large, high dimensional genomics and transcriptomic data sets, from both patient tumours and model systems. This includes advancing molecular profiling of cancer cells at single cell resolution4. Dr. Shah has been at the forefront of studying tumor evolution in breast, ovary and lymphoid malignancies. His work has been published in Nature, Nature Genetics, Nature Methods, NEJM, Genome Research, Genome Biology, amongst others. Dr. Shah oversees an annual budget of &amp;gt;$1M in competitively awarded funding from philanthropic, government and international bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other affiliations:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Faculty member, &lt;a href=&quot;http://bcbioinformaticsgrad.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CIHR/MSFHR Bioinformatics Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Faculty member, UBC &lt;a href=&quot;http://gsat.ubc.ca&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Genome Science and Technology Graduate Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Associate member, UBC &lt;a href=&quot;http://cs.ubc.ca&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Department of Computer Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Associate member, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bcgsc.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Michael Smith Genome Sciences Centre&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Adjunct Professor, SFU &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfu.ca/computing.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;School of Computing Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/myncbi/10i_ekwU-qiAU/bibliography/42630740/public/?sort=date&amp;amp;direction=descending&quot;&gt;View my collection, “My Bibliography” from NCBI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
